Byan: Hey, guys.
Soon | NTU: Hello, my hand.
Soon | NTU: Ongta no CI.
Soon | NTU: Are you on mute?
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Easwaran Jayaraman: Thank you, everyone.
germayne: Hey, hi, hi, Jayo.
germayne: Okay, we will… we will start soon.
germayne: How's everyone feeling?
germayne: This is the last official lesson. I think Saturday we are not… we are not going to have much content.
germayne: Sorry, sorry, Jagat?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Feeling a bit… Relieved, also.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: is coming in, because we are doing part-time course, right? If we do full-time course, it's different.
germayne: Oh, I heard, no, no, futon is even worse, I think.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yeah, yeah, so for part-time, managing the work with this has been a bit.
germayne: Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. No, I completely understand. I'm also feeling very relieved.
germayne: Yeah, it's been, it's been, it's been a great…
germayne: Is it 2 months? I think been with you guys 2 months, 2 months plus? More than two, more than that, I think.
germayne: Since March.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yeah, it has been moved.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Quite an experience.
germayne: Oh, yes, yes. Same for me as well.
germayne: No, but, it's not really the end for you guys. You guys still have…
germayne: You guys still have a bit more, a bit more to go.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, okay.
germayne: Okay, so I hope you guys are ready for the last… last… Official class.
germayne: for Module 3.
germayne: Okay, I will…
germayne: I will share my screen. I think today we have… we have a bit of content to go through.
Gwen Lim: Dee…
germayne: Okay, I will set, I will set the expectations, don't worry.
germayne: Okay, so, I think, I think, I think for… for…
germayne: Okay, guys, I think for 3.9, we didn't finish the exercise, right? We didn't have time to completely finish all of it, but I think looking at the content that we need to go through today.
germayne: So, I think we won't be continuing the 3.9, but if you guys have any questions, you guys can reach out, right? The code… the last part of the code should be quite self-explanatory, but just let us know if you have any questions.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so for today, right, I'm going to officially start the class. So today, I need to set some expectation with you guys.
germayne: Today, we are talking about… Not necessarily, like, the latest
germayne: technology, in a sense, but I would say it's relatively… new.
germayne: Compared to what we've gone through on 3.9.
germayne: So what we are talking about today, I would say, to some extent, some of it are just within the last 5 years. So what this means is that they are…
germayne: they are actually used by… still used by a lot of people in the industry, right? But what that also means as an expectation is that it won't be beginner-friendly.
germayne: Okay? I have tried my best to simplify the materials. We won't go through very, very deeply, because there's just no way I can cover
germayne: All of the latest stuff today.
germayne: But at least you will have an exposure on what it is. And I think one expectation to set is that given these are some of the more advanced stuff.
germayne: I would say it's okay if you don't understand everything today, and I think that is… that is an expectation to set, right? I will talk more about this on Saturday, about… I think, you know, after… after Module 3, what's next, right? Probably we can talk a bit more about that.
germayne: We will have some time on Saturday, so I'll focus more on, you know, from a perspective of what's next, right? And how do you actually continue learning? Okay, so obviously today is not the end of your learning journey. It shouldn't be.
germayne: And even after you have graduated.
germayne: You should continue to, you know, of course, if you are interested, you can continue to advance more into it.
germayne: All right.
germayne: So I just want to give the heads up first. The… we are really going through a lot of stuff.
germayne: Right? I mean, we don't have… we don't have…
germayne: any more modules left for Module 3, but the things that we want to unpack here, we are essentially going through, like, many years of advancement just in 3 hours.
germayne: Right? So it will, it will be…
germayne: not intuitive, it might be… it might take a bit, but I think if you have the videos, you guys can always revisit in the future.
germayne: Okay? So, so, I think it's fun.
germayne: Some of the latest stuff that is within the last 5 years, but will be challenging.
germayne: Okay, so… so what we are going to wrap off for Module 3, right, is that you guys already have the overview from, like, very basic foundation, right, from very simpler model, now all the way to very expressive models, right? 3.9…
germayne: shows the domain that you will be working on, which is natural language processing. Today, we are going to talk a bit about what are some of the links in utilizing, you know, NLP as a domain, but we're going to apply it back to deep learning. So we're coming back to deep learning again.
germayne: So this is the last series for deep learning, right? Last in the sense of, from a pedagogy perspective, it's usually taught at the end.
germayne: Okay, so it will be a bit confusing, and you will start to also realize that there's something that we'll be talking about, we are actually going back to sequential data, right? Because your natural language, as you saw in 3.9, is always a sequence.
germayne: Right, so we're going to apply this property in deep learning, and what this means is that today, if you think about the deep learning application, it's actually more on your sequential data, which means it's actually very relevant for 3.6, which is our time series, although we won't be using it on a time series domain.
germayne: Okay, so you can see we are going through a lot of stuff.
germayne: We'll talk a bit about… we'll recap
germayne: the application of deep learning on sequential data, and the first part will be on the recurring neural network. So it's a special upgrade to whatever that you guys have learned, right? Think of it like another computer vision module, right, where
germayne: Somebody has actually thought about
germayne: improving the neural network architecture in order to handle sequential data. And naturally, text data is sequenced.
germayne: We will then, of course, go on to the fun stuff, transformers, which are very relevant in terms of what powers some of the latest technologies today. Although it's not really new, I think it came out at least 5-6 years ago. Okay, but we'll talk about it.
germayne: And, of course, we'll end off towards
germayne: Moving on to some of the relation to… the generative models.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so I think I have set the context. At NLP, as you guys saw, the input data is sequential, right? Because your text data is sequential, but the task itself, at very high level, it is just a different form of classification task.
germayne: Okay, so it doesn't deviate from whatever that we have saw. We only saw that, largely speaking, at a broad level, whatever machine learning-related task is always either going to be classification or regression.
germayne: It's the same here, it is just that we package it.
germayne: we, you know, we think of a very smart way to express them as a classification problem. So you can see these are very common,
germayne: NALP task, your text classification, your name entity recognition, essentially.
germayne: we are just predicting some kind of labor for every token, right? We discussed this on… on Tuesday, and you will see, actually, it's really a form of classification based on the sequence data. You have the Q&A,
germayne: Which is also sort of, classification.
germayne: Summarization also is a kind of classification. Your text generation. Obviously, text generation you saw from your large language model. It's just predicting the next token.
germayne: We're not going to go much into style transfer, but we'll talk a bit about translation. So translation, basically, when you give an input in one language, you get to translate in other language. So you can see it's actually a subset of text generation. In fact, it is similar to text generation, architecturally, okay?
germayne: Okay, so we are going to go back to deep learning. We talk a bit about some of the classical stuff on Thursday, on Tuesday, if you remember. We talk about the TF-IDF, we talk about the vectorizer, we talk about how do you actually encode
germayne: the text data into some kind of vector representation, but we are thinking of it from a lexical perspective. What this means is that we are using the property of the text and the corrector itself on Tuesday, right? You guys have already seen this on Tuesday. Today, we are going to
germayne: You know, tied back to deep learning. What are the upgrades that we can make to deep learning so that it is actually able to process sequential data?
germayne: Okay? So we'll talk… we'll spend some time talking about it. We'll spend some time talking about the journey on how it has actually evolved.
germayne: And how we actually moved on to transformers today.
germayne: Okay, so you can see that for NLP, NLP is one of the fields that has evolved very rapidly. Just 5 years ago, a lot of stuff was done on
germayne: the traditional machine learning, people still do EDA, people, sorry, people still do feature engineering on all of the lexical features, but having said that, it doesn't mean that today we don't do it, okay?
germayne: there are still some of the use cases that are still used in the industry that we choose to do feature engineering and put it into some of the machine learning algorithms that you guys are familiar with. Because not everything needs to be deep learning.
germayne: Okay? So it doesn't mean it's useless, but the core limitation is that you guys can see that if you were to represent these using the TF IDF, for example, you'll expect that the vectors are sparse, because the dimensions need to be represented using your vocabs.
germayne: Correct?
germayne: Of course, you need to do feature engineering. NLP has reached a stage where deep learning models are good enough not to, you know, manually handcraft feature engineer… engineering features, right? And of course, one thing we want to talk about is the context of words.
germayne: the lexical method that we have used and talked about on Tuesday have no…
germayne: understanding of the context of words, which means semantic meanings are not captured, right? If people talk about fast food.
germayne: you will think about fast food like McDonald's, KFC, Burger King, etc. So you want to capture this kind of context, right? And obviously, you can't do it using lexical methods.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Which is why we want to use… Deep learning.
germayne: Which is why we can actually have the whole concept of
germayne: Using pre-trained models that has been transferred. Now, I want to ask you guys something.
germayne: We talk about using what people has trained on on a separate thing, and then use it on your own tasks.
germayne: Can you guys remind me what is it called?
germayne: So why is this… why is this thing where you're using other pre-trained models, and then you want to apply it on your own task?
Zac Ang: You may snap.
germayne: No, ImageNet is the model.
germayne: What, what is the, what is the, that, that, that, that mechanic?
Lily Seah: This dude is fun.
Teng Lee LIM: other lending.
germayne: Well, a lot of different answers. Okay, wait, Lily, yes.
germayne: This… okay, distillation is… Basically, taking a big model.
germayne: You want to use this big model's knowledge to train a smaller model.
germayne: But… so it's not wrong, but I think the one I'm asking is, let's say somebody, you know, used this model to train on, like, let's say, I think, Zach, you mentioned ImageNet, right? ImageNet is this data set.
germayne: Somebody used it to train on ImageNet, but then you want to use it to predict cats and dogs.
germayne: What is this thing called?
Zac Ang: Is it transfer learning?
germayne: Exactly. So we talk about transfer learning, right? So you'll start to see, right, the beauty of deep learning for NLP is not that you can just train it yourself.
germayne: That is not the… that's not the… that's not what makes it…
germayne: interesting today. What makes it interesting is that you can always transfer whatever someone else has trained on for their deep learning model, you can always apply it on your dataset. And even without training, the performance out of the box is really fantastic. So again, that's the… that is the theme that we are seeing here, which makes it
germayne: powerful, right? If, let's say, today, you have to retrain from scratch, I don't think it will be a big deal.
germayne: Alright?
germayne: Okay, so today we will have a few different terms. So, at the end of
germayne: Tuesday, we talk a bit about the word embeddings.
germayne: So essentially, we have this whole concept, and it's a recurring theme, right, that we saw in deep learning, where, given an input, we always want to learn about some representation of the data in some high dimension.
germayne: that concept has not changed, it's still the same, right? We always want to represent this input data.
germayne: Into some kind of high dimension.
germayne: we worked on the computer vision data, so if you remember, we worked on… okay, so I want you guys to help me, right?
germayne: I forgot. So what is the… what… what will, you know, in computer vision, how do I express my data? What is the matrix in the image data that we… that we do? Do you guys remember?
germayne: So N is the total number of images. What else do I have?
Teng Lee LIM: Pixel size.
germayne: Okay, so… so we have the height, the width, and what's the last thing?
Teng Lee LIM: the colors.
germayne: The channel, right?
Teng Lee LIM: Yep.
germayne: So, essentially, this is the data that we are working on in computer vision.
germayne: And you notice that we always want to represent them into some higher dimension.
germayne: representation, right? Going beyond the channel. So I believe it can be something like…
germayne: you know, the picture becomes very small, right, so we call it H', and then we have W prime, and then usually you have your last D, which is very, very big. The features that's extracted per kernel. So today, right, if you think about it, your text data is actually represented
germayne: in a sequence. So, you have n number of documents, right? We talk about documents, so each row is a document. For each document, you have a sequence of sentence, right? I walk a dot, that is a sequence of three, right? So you have your T sequence, right? And basically, this is your data, and actually, you have one.
germayne: Because you have one word per sequence.
germayne: Of course, I'm simplifying this, but the idea here is that this is your sequential data, right? You have T sequence, T tokens per document, and for now, we are just expressing them by 1, because there's only, you know, N by T.
germayne: So the idea here is actually very simple. You're going to do something similar. We are going to introduce a different mechanism where you want to learn some kind of hidden representation. So you're going to encode them into N by T by D again.
germayne: So you notice it's actually very similar, right? It's just that the process of doing it architecturally is different, and that is the whole lesson that we'll be spending on, okay, in terms of going through, but
germayne: central idea I want to talk about is when you think about embeddings, you always want to represent them into some kind of higher dimension, and once you can represent them in some kind of higher dimension.
germayne: A good analogy is as if the features are already engineered by the model. You don't have to do the feature engineering. So here is IDE features, right?
germayne: And then later on, you can put into your fully connected layer, you can do whatever you want. You can do your classification, etc, etc. Okay? Attention and transformer will come to that later, but attention mechanism is what powers the transformer architecture.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So… really, the emergence of deep learning model for NLP is that somehow, magically, somebody
germayne: pre-train the model on a specific task, and magically, somehow, it knows about the language. It knows about the context, and it captures the semantics of each of the words that you're putting in, which is why it's so powerful.
germayne: Yeah, so you can see right here, I think it's just starting to go recap, this is the same thing that we talked about on Tuesday, that your text data is a sequence. It has to be a sequence, right? Mary had a little lamp. It is a sequence data.
germayne: Does it make sense if I jumble the sequence? No, because if you jumble the sequence, the meaning of the sentence changes. What… how is this similar to time series? It's exactly the same, right? There's some kind of sequential structure, it needs to follow sequentially. So this is a sequence data.
germayne: And if you think about it, right, text generation as a task is actually predicting the next word. Sounds familiar, right? Mary, most likely, labor will be head.
germayne: And how this is actually formulated is that you're actually predicting a vocab, right? If you remember in your, you know, simplified example, in your TF-IDF, each of the columns is a vocab. V1, V2, all the way to VN.
germayne: Right, so what is this? We're actually predicting a classification problem. Given certain words, can I predict what is the highest probability of the vocab?
germayne: Right, so this is just one example for text generation.
germayne: And… Today, right, we are going to close the gap into
germayne: the next upgrade for deep learning. So, we're going to go back to… you know, for today, forget about convolutional neural network, because those were designed specifically to have the inductive bias of processing image data, right? Whole concept about image, again, was that we think about them locally.
germayne: This does not apply for… RN ends today. So today, right, the idea is that
germayne: We kind of want to introduce a new mechanism, where can we actually upgrade my…
germayne: Neural network in order to consider
germayne: the sequence of the sequential data, right? And, of course, if you… if you were to put it into a feed-forward neural network, it does not… you know, you can see here that it says that it does not capture the order and the context.
germayne: What this means is that if you think about your feed-forward neural network.
germayne: there's no way for me to express the data as a sequence, right? This is exactly the same problem for all the machine learning models. If you put in your X here, it has… it does not capture the sequence, because everything is just going to be treated as a separate role.
germayne: it will not care… it will not handle the sequential context. So you need some mechanism, very similar in time series, where you somehow want to express
germayne: the structure of the data, right? Now your data for the sequence will be N by T,
germayne: Which means that for every…
germayne: T sequence, T minus 1, T plus 1, we want that… we want the sequence to be handled, and therefore we need to think about a new mechanism to do that, and that's what we call the recurring neural network. So this is a level 1
germayne: upgrade that you will have, okay? We will start to do the upgrade today within the whole class. So from today, we will move from RNN all the way to Transformer, okay?
germayne: Yeah, so I think this is the… this is the… this is the thing that I was talking about. Image…
germayne: Inductive bias by the model is spatial awareness, right? Your kernel is always capturing
germayne: a specific portion of the image localized, right? And we strike the kernel across the image. We are teaching the model how to extract certain localized
germayne: features from the images, right? That's what we introduced. So today, we need to upgrade feet-forward neural network in order to force some mechanism to do
germayne: You know, to capture the sequence. You can see in here, there's no way the sequence is captured. It's treating everything as an independent input, which is not correct.
germayne: Oh, sorry.
germayne: Okay, so we are going to move on to recurring neural network.
germayne: Okay, so the recurrent neural network, essentially what we are doing is we are going to introduce this mechanism where we will somehow pass the context
germayne: from the previous sequence to the next sequence, okay? So, a very, very good way to think about it, right? I'm not going to go very deep. This is a fantastic block.
germayne: these GitHub pages. I used this in the past to understand it, so I'll leave the link here. But essentially, one of the mechanisms that introduced is that, if you think about it, right, X
germayne: going to A, going to an output of the hidden representation. If you think about it with a normal neural network, right, a normal neural network looks something similar, right? It would be something like…
germayne: your A is basically your weights, you put in your X, and then you get some kind of hidden representation. This is what we learned
germayne: Last week.
germayne: Right? This is what we learned last week. Now, the idea here is that this doesn't work because we were saying that, hey.
germayne: for sequence, obviously, the way to think about it is that, you know, I want some kind of context from the first sequence.
germayne: going to the second sequence, right? If I think about time series, I think about words, I need some kind of context that gets carried on, right? Whatever information I learn about 1 should be propagated to 2. Whatever I learn about 2 should be propagated to 3. Now, how do you actually update… upgrade this in a very simplest form? Basically, you just add a recurring
germayne: So you can see, this is, like, a recur… Recursive loop.
germayne: So I'm adding an arrow here. So essentially what I'm saying here is that, okay, let's just do a for loop, and then we just loop this repeatedly, right? If I put in the first input, I get a hidden representation from it. Hey, can we just hit… can we just feed that same representation back?
germayne: Right? For the second input. So now the second input has context from the first, as well as the context from the second input, right?
germayne: So, second, second, second, second time step.
germayne: Essentially, we'll have information from the… from the first.
germayne: Now, what this block actually expresses is that if you think about this structure, I can basically unroll this like a, like a…
germayne: like a picnic mat, right? I can basically unwrap this. So, instead of expressing this with a loop, right.
germayne: it's actually… it looks something like that. So this actually looks something like that. So if you think about it.
germayne: If I'm going to do a for loop here repeatedly, actually, all I'm just saying is that the model looks like that.
germayne: Can visualize, at this point.
germayne: Right? It is the same as just doing X0, go into A, produce hidden unit, and then actually this hidden unit is fit back, actually the arrow here is the same output. This hidden unit is actually fed back for the second, so you look at this, this is sequence number 1, index number 1.
germayne: Index number 1 has information not just from the input of 1, it has the context of the
germayne: output from 0. And we just repeat all the way, right? So basically, at the last time step, you have the T-1 that is going in here.
germayne: Right? And one property you'll notice is that the A is actually the same width.
germayne: Which means that our width doesn't scale according to the sequence.
germayne: Right? And if you look at this pattern, this pattern looks familiar. Very similar to our computer vision kernel, right? We use the same kernel, we apply the kernel, the kernel is getting updated.
germayne: So, same thing here. A here is actually basically your weight W.
germayne: what we are just saying is that we are just using this same W,
germayne: Right? But we are recursively adding the output from the previous sequence as an input for the next sequence. And that's it. That's basically the whole… I'm simplifying this a lot, but basically that is the whole idea of recurrent neural network. And of course, here you notice that the weights will be updated, and it will have information about each of the sequence.
germayne: Okay, and that's it. And you notice here that, actually, for each output, it will output different hidden units. So this is hidden, hidden unit for sequence 0, all the way to hidden units for sequence D.
germayne: So, assuming each hidden unit is D-dimensional.
germayne: What is the total output for each of the hidden units? Does anybody know?
germayne: Let me repeat again, assuming that your H is D-dimension.
germayne: How many of the D's I have here?
Josiah Ho: E. N.
germayne: Vision?
Josiah Ho: DN, as in… N as in… To whatever number.
germayne: Okay, you have N documents, so N is always ignored, we don't talk about N. So what's next?
germayne: Okay, we know D is the last one, right? Because there's… there's… every representation is D. How many Ds do I have here?
Zac Ang: T.
germayne: Exactly T.
germayne: So this is exactly what I've shown just now, right? N by T by D.
germayne: So you are able to express… for each of your sequence now, they have a hidden dimension.
germayne: Alright, so actually quite straightforward, right? Intuitively, you can see, huh?
germayne: there should be T number of D here, because there's T sequence.
germayne: Right? So if we stack them, basically we have T by D. Okay, ESX.
Zac Ang: I just want to ask, how is this different from the back propagation?
Zac Ang: Because you are also getting the learning backwards in back propagation, but you're just doing it differently here.
germayne: Okay, just to be clear, I think it's very, very different. When you say backpropagation, backpropagation is a process that we go backwards to update. Here, we are not going backwards. Here, I'm only going forward.
germayne: There's nothing that I'm going backward, so you see, we start with T, we start with X0, we go up.
germayne: Then after that, when we are done, this comes to here, we put in this, this is all going forward. We haven't gone backwards yet.
germayne: what you're talking about is something different. So what we talk about was, when we do backpropagation.
germayne: each of the widths needed to be updated, right? So here is W1, and here is W2. I'm using gradient descent to update from here. I'm going backwards to update. It's a very different thing. I haven't gone to backpropagation yet.
germayne: Does that… does that make sense? So don't be confused, we are always talking about forward first.
germayne: the backward will come later. I mean, we won't go very deep lah, it's more… it's much more complex. Okay, I'll talk about backwards later.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: But can arrive at this, okay, so I'll continue on.
germayne: Okay, so let's keep the N by T by D aside first, but the idea here is that for a typical recurring neural network flow.
germayne: has mentioned on the… on the lesson in… on Tuesday, you actually always need to tokenize your text. Basically, if you have a sentence, you need to tokenize them.
germayne: There are many various forms of tokenization, but usually in the recurring neural network.
germayne: case, one of the easiest ways to tokenize them is just basically split by the… the white spaces. So basically, you express… each of them has its individual word. And then what you need to do later on is that you actually need to express them in an embedding layer, right? Because neural networks cannot handle this, like, how can neural networks handle this?
germayne: So you need to put them into an embedding layer, which we discussed, actually, on… on Tuesday, right? Once you express them in your embedding layer, then you will do the learning in the sequence of
germayne: In the, in the recurring neural, recurring… the recurrent neural network sequence, okay?
germayne: So the recurrent neural network, essentially, this is the… this is the flow.
germayne: Yeah, I think I mentioned this into the embedding layer, okay? You need the embedding layer because you need to map, right? If, let's say, you have N by T,
germayne: Right? The T here, even after you tokenize, let's say if you were to tokenize it by white spaces, each of the T is still words, right? You still have something like I…
germayne: M…
germayne: Right? And on Tuesday, I mentioned about the embedding layer, so why don't you guys remind me what exactly is that embedding layer here? So, if n by t, the T is still different documents words, how will the embedding layer help? Do you guys remember?
germayne: So, example, this is Document 1. I am a…
germayne: After that, Document 2, you have Mary, Had…
germayne: So how can I put this into a neural network? I can't, right? Everything is still in words. So how does an embedding layer help?
germayne: Who can… who can guide me for the embedding layer?
germayne: So what… first thing is, what is the embedding layer? What was the term that I used? The embedding layer.
Zac Ang: convert words to numbers.
Zac Ang: to vectors.
germayne: Yes, so what… so how… what is it? How do I pres… how do I proceed? How do I mathematically… how do I work it out by hand?
germayne: So, if I were to create an embedding layer, what's the size of the embedding layer?
germayne: So, right now, I have n number of documents. Document number… document number 1 say something like, I am a blah blah blah. Document number 2,
germayne: Right? Mary had a little lamb.
germayne: So, now my M by T is like that, right? I tokenized already, but it still works. So, how will the embedding layer help?
Zac Ang: It converts it to Vectors.
germayne: Yeah, yeah, yeah. So what is the, what is the axis here?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Distance.
germayne: No, not distance.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: It's actually your fault.
germayne: It's your vocab size, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I will get slaves, yeah, Corey, we'll get slaves.
germayne: So it's the…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: V, the V.
germayne: Yeah, and then here is what?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, I remember it's D.
germayne: D, exactly. So what this means is that each, each row now is a specific word, right? So it can be I,
germayne: then this one is M, then all the universal vocab. So what happens is that all these are still words.
germayne: Basically, you just do a lookup, and then you convert them that, oh, I, I look up here, oh, is this D vector. So I replace I with D. M, I check this, okay, I replace this with this vector. So what happens is that, in total, you become N by T by D. This is before we even put into the neural network, it's already represented in D dimension.
germayne: Okay, your D, if let's say I represent there as 1, then it will be a simple case, right? But you can represent your D as any dimension. So now this is the input that we will put into the slide that we talk about.
germayne: Right?
germayne: In this, like… Right, we'll put the…
germayne: after you put into the embedding layer, now they are all in words. Sorry, they are now in numerical numbers, so then we can put everything through here.
germayne: Okay? So, I would say this, for the application perspective, this just takes certain experience, you'll see that it's the same format again and again, okay? It's the same format.
germayne: Again, same thing here, we set up the loss function to be cross-entropy.
germayne: Right? I think we went through the function already, I think it's 1 by N, 1 by C, summation, T, I, j, negative, log.
germayne: PIJ, right? We talked about this. Basically, this is the… this is the loss function for cost entropy for classification, right? So we're doing it. Atom, we didn't really talk about it, but atom is just another way to update your… your widths, right? The one that we've shown for gradient descent is the most basic one, but
germayne: there's actually a method of ADAM, which is empirically very, very popular and really very good. It maintains the… the… how is it different than the one that we thought? Is that it maintains the first and second order statistics in order to know how to upgrade the gradient. So it's a more powerful
germayne: method compared to gradient descent, right? But people typically use Adam, right? It's just a good practice.
germayne: Okay, so you can see… Just now, whatever that we went through, right?
germayne: I'll leave this to you guys lah. This is just a lot of details. But the whole idea here is that we haven't really talked about backpropagation, so I'll just go back.
germayne: Okay, so I'll just close off. Just now, Zach was asking, like, what about backpropagation? Okay, so you notice, right.
germayne: when we do forward, forward propagation means you are always just going through the neural network from your input to an output. So, same thing here. We are going through the neural network, so all your access are your raw data. You go in, you get an output, you go in. And you notice that it's forward because my data is going in. You see, I'm going in.
germayne: X2, X1 going in, followed by X2,
germayne: all the way to XT, and I get an output of 1 by n by t.
germayne: Sorry, N by T… oh, we are…
germayne: We can output at the end, N by T by D.
germayne: Right? N number of documents, T number of sequence, and D dimension, right? We get the output. Now, the question here is that you guys… you guys know this from Tuesday's lesson last week, that
germayne: the model is always initialized randomly, right? Your W is always random. And you notice we are using the same W, this is only 1W, there's only one W. It is only 1W, by the way.
germayne: Right
germayne: You notice that, obviously, when you do forward, you're not training the model, you need to do backward, right? So, there will be a same process. At the end, there might be some fully connected layer, there will be a loss. Now, you need to do backwards, right? We're obviously not going to go through the math. You guys want, I can give you guys the results later, but…
germayne: The idea is from the laws, it will flow backwards.
germayne: But can I… can I ask you guys, when I go backwards, do I start from…
germayne: Sequence 0, or do I start from sequence T?
germayne: So, when we go forward, we put in 0 first, followed by 1, so we do sequentially, right, 0, 1, 2, all the way to the last sequence. Now, we do backward prop, I'm going backwards, to update the weights. I want to update W,
germayne: who do I update first? Which, which weights, which…
germayne: Which… which sequence actually gets updated first?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: This is a bit tricky, right, because you have so many outputs.
Zac Ang: T.
germayne: But basically, what I'm just trying to tell you is that backwards will flow backwards, right? So now you'll start from the T portion, then it goes backwards.
germayne: Start from T, let it go backward. The only thing you need to take note is that this W is only one W, so you're actually updating the same W, but you're updating the same WT times.
germayne: Okay, but you flow backwards. So you can think of it as updating from sequence T all the way to sequence 1.
germayne: Okay, so that's backward. So you can see RD is backward, like that. So that's backpropagation, right? So you need to update your W here.
germayne: Okay, the backpropagation for RN, obviously, is more complex, we won't be talking about it.
germayne: But the intuition for you is that
germayne: the… the… the training step here is always the same, right? You always…
germayne: Okay, I mean, this is obvious. You, you usually… the… the neural network will automatically initialize for you. You fit in some output, you calculate the loss, and then you go backwards, update the weights.
germayne: repeat. It's the same… everything here is the same, nothing changes from the neural network. Same for computer vision models, same for fit-forward neural network, same for recurring, same for everything that we are talking about. Okay, so I'll just leave this slide.
germayne: Okay, I think before we end the RNN, it's just to tell you guys that, if you guys remember.
germayne: Just now.
germayne: Radar.
germayne: Oh, okay, wait, before I go on, yes, Teng Li?
Teng Lee LIM: That's how you were saying, right, for that propagation, right? Because the W will keep on changing, right?
Teng Lee LIM: And we go backward from T to 0.
germayne: -Oh.
Teng Lee LIM: So, then after that, we'll go forward again. So, the W that they will use to go forward will be the last W, is it?
Teng Lee LIM: Google Chrome.
germayne: Yes, yes, I know what you're saying. Okay, so if you think about the recurring neural network, you notice in this, in this, in this, in this graph, in this chart
germayne: I'm basically saying that this… this arrow here is like a for loop.
germayne: So, if I say that this arrow is a for loop, right, and then I roll it… I unroll, like, a picnic map into this, right? Actually, you notice that, is this W the same W or not?
germayne: It's actually the same W.
germayne: There's only one W, we are just repeating, putting into this W.
Teng Lee LIM: Hmm.
germayne: So, actually, your W is the same W.
germayne: But you're updating your WT number of times.
Teng Lee LIM: Yes.
germayne: Right? But you just go backwards, like that. Conceptually, you're going backwards, but I'm just doing a for loop.
germayne: T times.
germayne: Because there's only one W here. There's only one width.
germayne: If that makes sense.
germayne: So you can flow backwards, but the W is the same guy, so this is the same guy, you're just updating the same guy key times.
germayne: I'm simplifying it, like, obviously. The actual practice is not like that. I'm just simplifying the concept, yeah.
germayne: But you get what I'm trying to say, right? So, in the original neural network, obviously the W's are different, because you have different hidden units here. So you go here, you update W2, and then from W2, then you update W1, right?
germayne: In recurring neural network, the tricky part here is the W is the same W, there's only one W. Because in here, the arrow, you're just looping it, you're just looping it.
germayne: Right? But conceptually, when the flow comes backwards, we are actually flowing from sequence T, T-1, all the way to sequence 0. But because it's the same W, right?
germayne: Actually, the guide that's getting updated is the same. So, I come to here.
germayne: Hey, I'm updating W again. Okay, I come to here, I pass the gradient, oh, actually, I'm updating W again, all the way until the start.
germayne: Okay? So I think that's the… that's the takeaway. Don't need to go too deep lah. I don't think it's super important. My suggestion is to read the blog first, right, and get some understanding, but it's okay, you don't have to know the back propagation for this.
germayne: Okay, but the only takeaway I want you guys to be clear is that
germayne: Here, it might look very misleading that there's actually T number of weights, but the weights is only 1.
germayne: There's only one width.
germayne: Okay? And why do I say there's only one width? Because the original structure is an arrow here, right? We're just recursively doing a loop.
germayne: All right.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, so I think this is a… this is just an application… this is more on the application layer. So, if you guys remember just now, I mentioned that if you have a… if you have a data that is N by T,
germayne: at the end of the output of the neural network, you will get N by T by D, right? Because for each sequence, you have a hidden unit. Now, this… this is actually depending on your use case, right? It might get very confusing now, I don't go into too much details, but…
germayne: N by T by D, right, usually is the full output from the recurring neural network block. So in your, in your neural network, you have all the different LEGO blocks, right? So right now, the recurring, the RNN block, the one that I introduced to you.
germayne: Right? The RMM block is actually that same W, but we are just looping it like a for loop, just loop multiple times. So for each input, it just gives different D, right? So in total, you have N by T by D, actually, because you have each hidden unit that is generated per token.
germayne: But…
germayne: The final thing that you need to know is usually you add a fully connected layer at the end to learn something. You will always need to do a fully connected layer. This is a standard procedure that you guys have seen by now, right?
germayne: Depending on your problem statement, You will take different…
germayne: It will take a different subset of data from this N by T by D.
germayne: There's a one-to-one, there's a one-to-man… okay, one-to-one, obviously, is not important. One-to-one is basically the one that we learned in… on Tuesday. So, for recurring neural network, there's no one-to-one. Obviously, this is… this is not… that's not correct. One-to-one is basically your feed-forward, by the way? Feed-forward.
germayne: So for recurring, it's actually the rest.
germayne: Okay? So there are, there are many, there's one-to-many, many-to-one, many-to-many, man, yeah.
germayne: So, essentially here, the idea is that the output is N by T by D, Depending on your task.
germayne: Whether it's one-to-many.
germayne: many to one, many to many, it depends on your input data and what you expect out from the output. And that will affect the…
germayne: next block that you want to manipulate to pass on to the fully connected layer, okay?
germayne: this is really, really not very intuitive, okay? You, you need to… you need to… you need to have a bit of…
germayne: experience in looking at what are the different problems, and then you will then understand, but I would… I would say it's not super important right now. So, the idea here is that I just want to share with you guys
germayne: 1 to 1 is the… is the… you can see here, I already put a statement here that this is not RNN. 1 to 1 is basically what we have seen in…
germayne: on Tuesday, Feed Forward Neural Network.
germayne: Okay? One-to-many is an example where, let's say, if you do image caption, so an example, in this example, they put image caption. So, for image caption, right, you put in one input data.
germayne: But then you can use the recurring neural network block to output
germayne: T sequence of output, and it makes sense in this example for image caption. Because, example, you put in an image.
germayne: Your expected output is going to be a sequence of sentences. This… is… Dot.
germayne: Right? So what this means is that you expect the… you're expecting to use each of the hidden units from the recurring neural network, right? So you're going to use each of the D.
germayne: In order to generate the text.
germayne: You can also do many-to-one, which means you put in… you put in your sequential data, which means you put in your text, and then you do a classification. So something like that can be something like your sentence classification, because you have a sequence of sentences, N by T,
germayne: I want to predict whether, given this sentence, whether it's a positive sentiment, whether it's a negative, whether… so you realize that actually you only need one output. So what people usually do here is that when you have your recurring block, right, your recurrent block here.
germayne: Just now, I mentioned that your recurring block is N by P by D, right?
germayne: So what people usually do is, instead of taking T number of hidden units, you just take one.
germayne: You just take the last one.
germayne: So, what you do is you don't care about the others that has been outputted, you take the last one, right? The intuition here is because the last one has already contained the context of everything from everyone. So I just need to take the last one, I flatten this into M by D,
germayne: and I put it into a… Fully connected layer.
germayne: Okay, so this is very similar, right? If you notice this, right, is actually very similar to when we do the image classification. So M by D, and then you just put into your fully connected layer.
germayne: Okay? You don't have to know this, to be honest. I think right now it might feel very, very confusing, but I think the important point here is that it's just very flexible, right? And that's how it powers the, you know, text. You can do text generation, you can do single output classification, and then, of course, you have the last one, which is many-to-many.
germayne: Which is, like, things like translation tasks.
germayne: Right? So your many-to-many, you can see here, is like your translation, right? And you can see here, the intuition is because if you put English here, you put an English sentence, you output something in Spanish.
germayne: is going to be a sequence, right? So you expect a sequence to come out, so it's many-to-many. So here, you use a full representation of the
germayne: the hidden units per token, right? And by T by D, we just put everything else. So you can have the machine translation.
germayne: And then, your NER, the one that we talked about, for every sentence, every token, sorry, every token, you want to predict whether it's a person, it's a location, it's a human, it's a dog, whatever, your NER task, right? That one is also many-to-many, because
germayne: Your final output, what you expect is going to be N by T by V.
germayne: Sorry, not… not V, huh? Let me, let me remove this. By C.
germayne: So, I'll explain this, right, M by T by C. So, example, if you guys remember, I gave that example where, let's say you have a sentence, I am…
germayne: a dot.
germayne: So for NERR tasks, I think Kendra was asking on Tuesday, so for each one, you'll predict, what is this? Is this a dog?
germayne: human…
germayne: blah blah blah, right? So it is an error. So you notice that, actually, for each one, I have a class, right? So imagine here, I want to predict dot or human, there's two classes. So for each token, I have two…
germayne: Correct? So this is the shape of the final output.
germayne: each document for T-Sequence.
germayne: I want to predict whether human or dog, so there's a tool here. So that is the example for these many-to-many.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, if you ask me, is it very important right now? I don't think so. Okay? When you want to do the task, you can easily just follow a guide, right? But the idea here is just that RNN, I'm just trying to express, is very flexible.
germayne: Okay, and I just decided to give this example for machine translation. So, machine translation…
germayne: Let's… in this example, we have… Attacks.
germayne: Right? We put into the recurring neural network, you pass the context here, we decode it, and then we… we output the final… the final output to translate it to English.
germayne: So you notice here is many, right? Many sequence. Then you, you do text generation, many output.
germayne: Okay, so this is the… this is the many-to-many.
germayne: many to many here. And they call it the encoder-decoder model.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: encoder… You guys realize this is not the first time that you heard it.
germayne: Right, the word, the term end quote. End quote is always…
germayne: Put into some kind of representation?
germayne: Learn about the context.
germayne: Decoder just basically means that you got the hidden context, I'm just going to use it to output.
germayne: Very confusing, I know, but decoder… encoder, decoder, very typically, people use it for machine translation tasks. It's a very specific term that is used in machine translation.
germayne: Okay? But we'll talk about this encoder-decoder later again. Okay? It's been used in different areas, different contexts. Talk about it later.
germayne: Okay, so don't worry, we'll come back to encoder-decoder later.
germayne: Okay, I… I will give a pause here, right? I give you guys a warning already, right? By the way, we are just warming up money. It's going to get even harder later on. The… the matrix…
germayne: thing you will need time to go through. You will not understand it based on what I have today, right? I mean, I can explain it because I understood it already, but…
germayne: If you need to, my advice is that you go and try it out from the application standpoint, then you will understand how the shape matters.
germayne: Okay? So if you cannot get it at this point in time, I think it's okay. It's not simple. These are… these are very complex.
germayne: topics that we are going through. Okay, but end takeaway, right, if you guys don't really want to go away, the end takeaway here is just to understand, let's say if there's only one takeaway you want to have, is to at least just understand
germayne: this… And this.
germayne: And that's it. Okay, I think that should be the minimal takeaway.
germayne: The rest is all slightly more advanced. So I'll leave this one to many, many to many here, so when you guys need, you guys can come back and revise, and maybe just watch the video again, right? Then you will understand why it requires this.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Any, any other questions so far?
germayne: I see that there are some questions that are being asked.
germayne: Ian, does that… does that answer your question?
germayne: Okay, so when I say it's harder, it's harder, right? Agree? So far? Is it more challenging?
germayne: Oh, yeah, Zach.
Zac Ang: Oh, sorry, I got a question about the type of RNNs. Just now you said that one-to-one is not an RNN, it is…
Zac Ang: speed forward propagation.
germayne: No, no, no, no, no, no, don't use the propagation. Propagation is only used when you are training the model to update the weights.
germayne: One-to-one is basically the same thing that we learned on Tuesday, because you have one… you have one X. There's no sequence, per se.
germayne: Right? There's no concept of sequence. Your data here is usually N by… n by d, right? Based on the number of features you have. There's no concept of sequence. You put into here, the final output here usually is going to be something like n by… n by 1 for regression.
germayne: or it's going to be N by C for classification. So you notice that there's no concept of sequence, so it's one-to-one.
germayne: Understand?
germayne: Right, so here.
germayne: the point of putting this here is to show that, actually, your RNN, right, is just an expanded version of 1 to 1. So, you might see, you know, the fun fact, right, that I want you guys to go back with is that if you look at it, right, it might look like, oh my god, why is this so complex? But the thing is that under the hood is a for loop.
germayne: you know, as complex as this looks like, this is a for loop. You guys know what for loop is, right? Right now? I'm just looping this, and then I loop this, and I loop this. And the takeaway here is that, why is it a for loop? Okay, so, I'm going to give a few additional things that I didn't talk about. So, you notice that something is actually interesting here.
germayne: Firstly, we are saying that sequential data needs to be respected, that's why we are processing the data one by one. Now, I want you guys to… I want to ask you guys this thing from an intuition. I say it's a for loop, right?
germayne: So, what is the takeaway from here?
germayne: What's the drawback of this architecture?
germayne: What was the problem here?
germayne: Without talking about the complex stuff, what's the first intuition that you think about? If I say it's a for loop, what does that mean?
Zac Ang: The follow-up can go on forever, how do you know where to stop?
germayne: No, I mean, you'll stop at the last sequence lah, you'll stop at the last sequence.
germayne: But what I'm trying to say is that
germayne: we are moving from this guy to this guy. You notice it's not much of an upgrade. It's almost similar. We're just adding a for loop to just look
germayne: iteratively for 0, then 1, then 2. So, when you think about a for loop, right, what's the thing that you'll think about? So, you see, notice that I'm saying that it has to be done sequentially. What does that mean?
Zac Ang: It'd take a long time.
germayne: Yeah, so you see, I think Brian gave the answer. So basically, it's sequential, right? Sequential means that I cannot do this in parallel, I cannot, like, say that, oh, if let's say I got T sequence, I can't just do all of them at once. I have to do one, all of them one by one, right? I do this, then I do this, then I do this. So you notice that there's always this bottleneck.
germayne: that I have to do this loop here.
germayne: And it's very important that you take away this intuition, because
germayne: Then, later on, when we start to see that, oh, later on, when we start to see other architecture, then you're like, oh my god.
germayne: Why is other architecture used instead of recurring neural network? Understand?
germayne: Right? So when I say it's a for loop, right, it means that it cannot… it has to be done. Okay, now I want to ask you guys a question. Is there something else that we learned in the class that is something similar? That something is done sequentially?
germayne: We learned this in the class, and you guys applied this on Kaggle.
germayne: What was it? What was it that's sequential?
Teng Lee LIM: Radiant boosting.
germayne: Exactly, we talked about gradient boosting, right? Although, theoretically, they have done some smart way to do that, but your boosting algorithm is sequenced, right? Your weak learner is always learning from a previous learner. It cannot be done in parallel.
germayne: So, you can see there's a similarity in here.
germayne: Okay? So, very important for this. Takeaway here, I just want you guys to know, right, it looks very complex, but the code is actually just a loop. It has to be a loop. There's nothing smart about this.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: All good.
germayne: All good, right? Okay, I will tell you guys what are the important points. The more challenging one, in terms of the type of RNN, is just really how you design the architecture to take into the data, but you do not need to recreate these. These are already done. Let's say if you want to do any, you want to do any other tasks.
germayne: you can just do a Google for NER, you want to see recurring, you'll definitely get a quote example of how to do it, but the idea here is that people has already formulated this, so you don't have to do this.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so I think we'll… we were, we will… we were… okay, so I think what? We'll take a short 5 minutes break, hot, short 5 minutes water break to drink water, bio break. We come back at 8, and soon we'll just go through the collab notebook.
germayne: To just showcase on the application part for…
germayne: RNN before we go into the very, very hard stuff, okay? Just get radii, it's gonna get harder.
germayne: Amazing.
Soon | NTU: Brian? Jimmy?
germayne: Yeah, yeah, yes, yes, yes, bro, yeah, soon.
Soon | NTU: No, it would do, no, after the… Oh, okay.
germayne: Okay, yep.
Soon | NTU: Kidding.
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: To me, I've got one question.
germayne: Wait, who is this?
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: Adrian.
germayne: Yes, Adrian, go ahead.
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: It's just now you got one slide, you say that what is not correct? Is the illustrations on the slide is not correct?
germayne: Oh, okay, okay, okay, sorry, sorry, I don't… I shouldn't use that word. It's just this, it's just this.
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: Yeah, because if it's not correct, then we shouldn't…
germayne: No, no, no, no, it's not that, it's no, no, it's not that it's wrong, it's not that it's wrong. I'll rephrase, I'll rephrase again.
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: No, I think one more slide.
germayne: No, it's this is this. It's the same, it's the same, this one, this one. So basically, the 1 to 1 here, I already put, this is not RNN. I put it here in…
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: Okay.
germayne: It's not that it's wrong, it's just that what you're trying to illustrate here is that
germayne: the RNN, the one-to-one is the simplest example that we learned. It's not an RNN, but it's just put here to illustrate the difference.
germayne: Okay. Yeah? Yeah? Okay, it's not as wrong, I think I used the wrong word, yeah.
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: Okay, thanks.
germayne: -
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Go ahead, go ahead.
germayne: Go ahead, yes.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You mentioned, when you mentioned follow-by, it's not because,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I know follow, you can… I mean, I'm not sure if follow is a good image, imagery, yeah, because…
germayne: Why?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because for loop, right, you can also jump out of the for loop.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, in this case, you can't, right, because it seems you mentioned… because you want us to take away that.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Sequential is very important. That means… that means for this, this RNN, right, you start over here, it must… it must always finish at the end on it.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Or you cannot help… they say there are 10, there are 10, but I finished 2. I come out, cannot.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: And I didn't.
germayne: No, cannot, cannot.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, not right. So I gotta do all right. That's what you mean by sequential, is it?
germayne: Exactly, yeah. I mean, the code is hard-coded to look through the sequence lah, so it will need.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, but once you start means you're not gonna halfway backlog order or stop. You have to go all the way to the end, that's what it means by sequential,
germayne: Yeah, but it's the same point.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because, yeah, I was wondering whether follow is the right, is a good imagery, because it might not be, yeah, because…
germayne: No, no, but for loop is correct, because in the code, right, the block is the… the LEGO block is the same LEGO block. So what I'm just trying to express here is that, from a code perspective.
germayne: If you were to write a recurring… the recurrent neural network from scratch, right.
germayne: I'm not redesigning an architecture, you see. This is… this expression, right, is just an expression where we are just handling the sequence, but in your code, right, it's just going to be…
germayne: for… I all the way to T.
germayne: I'm going to take X, I'm just simply… okay, I'm simplifying it, I'm simplifying.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Bye.
germayne: How about a week?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I know, I know.
germayne: simplifying it, the function for recurring, obviously, is more complex, but let's say, you take W, you dot product with X.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: What do you do next?
germayne: You look to the next one, you take the Z, you take the same Z, you dot product with the X again.
germayne: You're just looping these T times. This is how the code looks like.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But in a way, what I'm saying is that the… you… in a sense, it's correct, lah, you look…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: N times, or T times.
germayne: T times, T times…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Tea time, but you… but you cannot halfway through the…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So I know, like, T minus, 33, T minus… T minus 3 times you come out. Well, why would you come out?
germayne: Why you wanna come out? Why you wanna come out?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Paul Lu, usually when you come to… when you meet certain conditions that you want, you just come along.
germayne: No, but the architecture here is that you want to process the T sequences
germayne: Right? All the data I want to process forward.
germayne: So why, why you want to come out halfway?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Well, I was thinking that, you know, since you say it's a for loop, then I can come out lah, but it's not exactly a for loop, because I've got to start from beginning to end, mah. So now I know that for loop is not exactly correct, lah.
germayne: No, I understand that.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Stuff from beginning to end all the way lah, right?
germayne: Yes, yes, yes.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: That's what it means
germayne: all I'm just trying to express is that the, this, this thing, right, is not… is not that it's introducing something new, it's the same thing. It's just that when they wrap it like that.
germayne: It's just a for loop. And if you think about it as a for loop, it's actually not as… not as scary, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, I know it's scary, but it's easy to throw some misconception inside, that's what I try to…
germayne: No, no.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I understand that.
germayne: Yeah, yeah, but I think it's the way you understand.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, they are.
germayne: Yeah, it's different.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I do follow, I can always come out one.
germayne: But it's a for loop, by the way. If you look at the code, the code written is a for loop. They look with the sequence.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So is this different from the epoch that we talked about,
germayne: This is within… this is different, this is within the sequence. Your epoch is the outside training loop. So, your outside training loop, right, so, okay, so a good question, by the way. So, in your outside training loop, right, the loop, the first loop is going to be… your first for loop is epoch.
germayne: Your second for loop is iteration, because this is your total number of data set.
germayne: Your total N divided by your batch size.
germayne: in your recurring, right, there will be another for loop, because now you'll be looping for every T sequence, so now there's 3 loop
germayne: So it's 4… 4… 4.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: No, the first one is Epoch, the first one is Epoch.
germayne: Yeah, first one, Epo, second.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Or that's the iteration, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, it's recent.
germayne: And so this is the same as what we learned, it's the same…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Wow, very complex now,
germayne: Yeah, exactly, that's what I'm saying. And by the way, we're only getting warm up, huh? This is the easiest… this is the easiest of today. We're only getting warm… we're only warming up. It's going to get harder.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Bakita, let's see how…
germayne: Yeah, but don't be afraid of it, lah, I think it's just knowing it. You can always come back later.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, I guess it's trying to understand the concept, you know, otherwise it's like… Yeah, you'll get lost.
germayne: You need time, you need time to go back and learn it.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: And digest it, huh.
germayne: Yeah, you need time, yes. Okay, I think it's it ready. I can take any questions later on, but let's continue with the…
germayne: the…
germayne: That exercise. You will notice that when you apply using PyTorch, it won't be as complex, because you're not writing from scratch, it's already written for you. You don't need to…
germayne: But if you want to write from scratch, then you have to write the for loop lah, right? But, yeah.
germayne: Okay, yeah, I'll hand over to Sun.
Soon | NTU: Thanks, Jimmy.
Soon | NTU: Great. Can you see my screen?
Soon | NTU: Okay…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: 3.10.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, Sifu Montene.
Soon | NTU: I'm, sharing with you the GitHub, the 3.10, repo. Okay, let me…
Soon | NTU: Resize the window a bit.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, so this, module is a bit different in that it has no,
Soon | NTU: folder, right, in the… in the GitHub.
Soon | NTU: Right? The repo, okay? But in order to go to the Jupyter Notebook, right? Okay, so please go to 3.10, the repo, and then…
Soon | NTU: lesson.md.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so where we have the content of our 3.10 NLP Advanced lesson, okay? So, on this page, right, you can see a link, okay?
Soon | NTU: To bring you to this, collab, for… to open the notebook, right? Now, the reason why
Soon | NTU: we need to do this is… now, should you, let's say, intend to run this for your, let's say, testing purpose, okay, just want to see how the code works, right? You…
Soon | NTU: Please don't run it on your…
Soon | NTU: local… your laptop, right? Okay, because,
Soon | NTU: I tried that before, okay? So it took me,
Soon | NTU: two and a half hour to complete, right? So I was just curious, so I just attempted to do this. But anyway, in order not to waste so much time on this, okay, so you can click on this link.
Soon | NTU: Right? So I believe all of you have a…
Soon | NTU: some, set up your collab already, right? Okay, so that will bring you to this, page, okay? So I, I already have,
Soon | NTU: the pitch here. Okay, so… now, this…
Soon | NTU: page, right? This notebook is, read-only, right? So if you want to make use of these, the codes.
Soon | NTU: Right? To run the codes.
Soon | NTU: you have to save it in your own drive, whether is it Google Drive or GitHub, right? So…
Soon | NTU: by… you… you should know by now, right? Okay, so, for me, I will just save a copy in Drive. Okay, anyway, the instruction is,
Soon | NTU: already given in the, I think in the lesson.md, okay? So you need to save this.
Soon | NTU: a copy in… Drive, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, and then you,
Soon | NTU: Do your whatever testing using a copy of this, okay, under your own account, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… Let me go to this…
Soon | NTU: Because I have already run it once, right?
Soon | NTU: So let me go to the… at least, as I show you the code, I have some kind of output. I think the,
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the original version also has some output lah. Okay, put our… use my own,
Soon | NTU: Copy to explain to you.
Soon | NTU: Okay? So… Right.
Soon | NTU: or you can go all the way, okay, because all these are… the first part is sharing with you the basics of this, deep learning network relating to the NLP, right?
Soon | NTU: Duh.
Soon | NTU: why is NLP, you know, what are the application and use cases, and so on. And,
Soon | NTU: Jermaine has shared the R&N. Okay, so the first
Soon | NTU: A thing which we are going to do is to review
Soon | NTU: the code for this INN to see how we can, make use of this PyTorch to implement the INN model.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then we will use a trained model to do some, text generation.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is, basically nothing but just to disable some, I think some logging feature, right?
Soon | NTU: So this is,
Soon | NTU: just for performance reasons, make sure that your code is not hogging just because of something in the background is running, right? This is a WID environment, this is, some kind of a…
Soon | NTU: library.
Soon | NTU: that may…
Soon | NTU: By default, it may be on, okay, so just in case. So, we will explicitly disable this feature.
Soon | NTU: Okay, before we continue. Now, this, you know, PyTorch.
Soon | NTU: I would say the Hugging Face data set, right? So, some of them are, maybe quite, huge, okay? So, for performance and efficiency reasons, okay, so the, the, the training data are actually, were cache
Soon | NTU: meaning to temporarily store in your local drive, okay? So, you may only need to download your dataset once, okay? So, but in the process, if you are storing a copy in your laptop, right.
Soon | NTU: You will not have this concern on, let's say, file being locked by more than one user, because if you do it only on your laptop, okay, no such concern on your file locking, but if you do it in the, maybe a production environment, multi-user, okay, so potentially there could be
Soon | NTU: a multi-user accessing the same file. Okay, so this is basically just, some, package to… allowed,
Soon | NTU: this, PyTorch, right, to manage this kind of,
Soon | NTU: prevent record locking, you know, in case more than one user is assessing the same data set at the same time, okay? It will not happen to us.
Soon | NTU: Because our copies… Local in our drive.
Soon | NTU: Okay, now, if you, after this, we may… you may need to restart your runtime, right? Meaning that you…
Soon | NTU: Go to this.
Soon | NTU: Oh, sorry.
Soon | NTU: King.
Soon | NTU: Because, you start your session, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so restart session is to restart your runtime. Now, So Let me continue.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we need to install the dataset of For the… the demo.
Soon | NTU: Okay, in this, Jupyter Notebook, the IAN demo. Okay, so I think Hugging Face has already
Soon | NTU: chop this word, dataset, right? It's not hugging face underscore dataset, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you see data set like this, you know this data set belongs to the tagging phase. Now, within this datasets, right, there are actually a lot of, sub…
Soon | NTU: grouping and category of data, okay? So, you actually have imported a lot of things
Soon | NTU: From the tracking phase,
Soon | NTU: library, okay? So, you know, it works the same way as the other, like, Seabourn, you know, those libraries that have a built-in, data set, okay? So.
Soon | NTU: This is how they work, right? And then you import the necessary library.
Soon | NTU: In the case of PyTorch, right, data set and data logger.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and also the dataset, right? It provides a load dataset, some kind of a function for you to load the data set, specific data set that you need to, use for your model training.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: So, in this case, we are using this, PTB.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so it is… it stands for… Pain…
Soon | NTU: three bank data sets. Okay, so it's contained, About… is it 20,000?
Soon | NTU: of,
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… so you can… you can go and check it out, okay? So it's actually, some…
Soon | NTU: article about… Wall Street Journos.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is, this data set, right, it contains both training, validation, and tests.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this… So later, you need to split it into 3 portions.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you print out the content of this data set, you notice this is a dictionary of,
Soon | NTU: Dictionary of dictionary.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let's see…
Soon | NTU: what is… how does the first three, samples in the training data look like? Okay, so a… something like this.
Soon | NTU: Yay.
Soon | NTU: I'm not sure what language is this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so any… anyone know?
Soon | NTU: Okay, is it, is it… Alright, yeah.
Soon | NTU: doesn't seem to be in English, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, anyway, without, looking at this, the actual content, okay, so this is how the structure of your training data looks like. Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: It is, containing, actually, a dictionary of… With only a sentence.
Soon | NTU: The key, lookup key is the sentence, and then the content of that sentence, okay?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is a tokenizer, just to… show you…
Soon | NTU: How the tokenizing… tokenizer function works, because we are going to use this
Soon | NTU: In our… when we build the vocabulary using this.
Soon | NTU: PTB, the corpus, okay, training data, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so as you can see, We look up this.
Soon | NTU: Basically, we are putting all this thing and put everything
Soon | NTU: checking for the unique words, right? And then forming the vocabulary like this, okay? So, out of so many, articles in this dataset, right, training data set, we have
Soon | NTU: Unique Woods.
Soon | NTU: Vocab size, right? About Close to 10,000 words.
Soon | NTU: Something like this, okay? So now, there is a listing of the vocabulary, like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so each vocabulary has…
Soon | NTU: a unique index, right, integer index that is associated with it. Okay, let me go all the way.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: So, the first one is, unknown. Okay, so just to… in case there is, there are some words which are not found in the vocab, okay, so that will be tagged with the UNK
Soon | NTU: Short for unknown.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Doing the, -Oh.
Soon | NTU: Training, and also prediction, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you have added something extra here in the first item of your vocabulary. Okay, so now this vocabulary size is specific to our
Soon | NTU: PTB data set.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so with this.
Soon | NTU: Because vocabulary is a list of unique words, right, of the corpus, okay? So now we are going to this, encode function, okay? We are going to the individual, the articles, okay? And then.
Soon | NTU: form.
Soon | NTU: the index.
Soon | NTU: That means…
Soon | NTU: If the word found… let's say it's a word, it's a group, okay, so we will put this 48
Soon | NTU: into the…
Soon | NTU: word position, okay, and then so on, for every word that you found in your corpus, okay? It's a continuous, long list of,
Soon | NTU: Numbers for the whole corpus, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, up to here, any question and doubt on the… on the logic.
Chieh Cheng Lai: I have one question. So, just want to mention the unknowns words. So, unknowns words, I mean, we have many unknowns words, so it will be classified as a zero, in this case.
Soon | NTU: Yes, yes. I suppose the… you won't find it during training because you have already put it in your vocabulary, okay? Because your training data built the vocabulary, right? So, not likely that you have words in your training data
Soon | NTU: Not found in your vocabulary, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you will probably find words in your test data or validation data that are not found in your vocabulary. So in those… for those words, right, you will tag those words with UNK.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Otherwise, you will be… the model will not know how to And those are a whiz.
Soon | NTU: Yes.
Gwen Lim: Can I ask, so if you're looking to create a specialized model using NLP, the library that we then therefore use would be, semantically weighted towards terms
Gwen Lim: more occurrence of terms in the library. For example, if it's engineering, there'll be more things about engineering terms. Is this correct?
Soon | NTU: More terms of engineering, okay, the scope of the topics all depends on this
Soon | NTU: PDB. We are training our language model from scratch.
Gwen Lim: Okay.
Gwen Lim: So then, if we wanted to specialize.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, so later, we will use this book to, as, illustration, as a demo, to show you how we can actually train a language model, not right from scratch like this.
Soon | NTU: Based on… our starting point is the pre-trained model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, yeah, so because we did not do that in the CNN, okay, so let's do it in the NLP, okay?
Soon | NTU: There are only a few things that you need to…
Soon | NTU: To adapt in order to leverage on the existing or the pre-trained model.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me go to… Okay, so we have built the vocabulary.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so it's to prepare us to train the model, right? We already have the vocabulary, right? We already have the first dimension of some
Soon | NTU: wood and bailing. Okay, so we need to have the second dimension, right?
Soon | NTU: Which is the size of our, embedding, again, meaning the feature that we want the model to learn, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… We are here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we usually have to, you know.
Soon | NTU: possible, try to build our logic in the form of a class, right? Because that will make our code very usable, right?
Soon | NTU: So, in this case, we have this sequence. We define two, parameters for our class, okay?
Soon | NTU: attribute, what I'll call it, okay? The first one is a sequence length, and the second is a batch size, okay? Sequence length is, like, because our corpus, right.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, it's not conta… it's not containing a multiple sentence anymore, okay? We have already…
Soon | NTU: Put everything into one long list of numbers like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now…
Soon | NTU: What you need to do is, you need to, of course, it's good to process things in batches, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so in this case, not only batches, but we have some kind of a sliding window within a batch.
Soon | NTU: Agreed.
Soon | NTU: In addition to the patch, not within the batch, okay? So this sequence length is actually the number of token that you select.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and then each of these 30 sequence, 30 tokens, right, okay, you will shift it by one.
Soon | NTU: Okay, as you can see here.
Soon | NTU: Right? The reason why we do this is, okay, so we are actually leveraging on this kind of logic, right?
Soon | NTU: The first sequence is our training data, okay? We shift it by…
Soon | NTU: One position, okay, to derive our target.
Soon | NTU: Because our concern is only to predict the next row in the sequence.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so in this manner, you can form, actually, a lot of, this kind of,
Soon | NTU: Input and labor sequence.
Soon | NTU: For the training.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And then this branch size is,
Soon | NTU: That, that, that window, okay? You…
Soon | NTU: Now you split this total training data into batch side of 64.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the next, class definition is for us to define how our IN model looks like, right? So, basically, we have some, standard parameter, okay?
Soon | NTU: Absolutely defined, okay? So, we may choose to implement one RIN model with a fixed embedding size.
Soon | NTU: Cannot be mortified, you know?
Soon | NTU: 64, 64, you cannot choose 1, 2, A, and so on, okay? So, that are… those are the parameters you…
Soon | NTU: can…
Soon | NTU: define when you create your INN model, okay? So now, we have the embed size, vocab size, embed size, and hidden size. So, to make everything simple, right, the INN only have one hidden layer, okay, with
Soon | NTU: Okay, let's look at this, right?
Soon | NTU: Our vocab size, we have already determined before is 9644, right?
Soon | NTU: 9644, inclusive of the unknown wood, right? So the embed size is… what is embedding size?
Gwen Lim: Is that meaning 8x8?
Soon | NTU: Okay, we are now doing wood and bedding, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we know we have, 90,000 over… close to 10,000 words sold.
Soon | NTU: We had the first dimension, This tuber, right?
Soon | NTU: This is the… second dimension.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the D, as this search engine may always use.
Soon | NTU: the D. So, every word has 64,
Soon | NTU: Vectors are a number, okay, which are the feature for… To, to…
Soon | NTU: To represent the meaning of that particular, tokens.
Soon | NTU: Token or width.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the hidden size.
Soon | NTU: Only one layer in… and the hidden side has, 1, 2, 8 nodes.
Soon | NTU: Then, to create our INN model, we just simply call this statement, and… specified across entropy loss N.
Soon | NTU: to optimize them.
Soon | NTU: Why cross-entropy loss?
Soon | NTU: You know, if you predict the word, next word right, you probably have, maybe, more than one choices.
Soon | NTU: a few choices, right? So that will give you the, you know, chance. You only pick the one that is,
Soon | NTU: high… highest, probabilities, right? Okay, so we are not looking at binary cost enthalpy.
Soon | NTU: Okay, no.
Soon | NTU: If we want to make use of a pre-trained model, right, so likely that
Soon | NTU: we need to make use of, GPU.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… if you can run, complete the training, process using CPU, okay, go ahead, but…
Soon | NTU: the reason why we are doing it in the collab is because it's gonna be very, time-consuming to run this, okay? Now, this statement is to check whether you have,
Soon | NTU: the GPU, or only have CPU, okay? So if you do not have a GPU, right?
Soon | NTU: Unless you have time lah. Try not to run it yet.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that will give us a CUDA and…
Soon | NTU: You may have more than one cool down, okay?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is the… We've got collab, so we have a GPU there.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Now, the training function…
Soon | NTU: Okay, we will leverage on this data loader from the PyTorch, right, library, okay, to manage all this, the data loading, the batching.
Soon | NTU: For us, okay? Now, one thing to take note that is, in order for you to train your model, okay, your model and your data have to be located in the same device.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is something… Additional when you need to.
Soon | NTU: Use a pre-trained model.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Now, if your device is CPU, of course, this statement still works.
Soon | NTU: You just move whatever data.
Soon | NTU: back to the same location, okay? Nothing wrong with that, okay? The only, difference is, you have to make sure that this
Soon | NTU: Model is in… If you move this tool.
Soon | NTU: a model to a device. You have to do this to your input.
Soon | NTU: data as well.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Otherwise, you will have, some error, runtime error, when you try to run it during training.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so everything pushed to the device before we start our training process. Again, back to our very standard, five-step,
Soon | NTU: so-called the process for training using PackTorch, right?
Soon | NTU: 0 is the gradient.
Soon | NTU: So this is the… forward pass.
Soon | NTU: Determine what… quantify the loss using the loss function.
Soon | NTU: Backward publication, and then adjust the…
Soon | NTU: Weep and biases to prepare for the next, training iteration.
Soon | NTU: I would say matching the expansion, right?
Soon | NTU: So, we will look at the, average, loss.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Per the whole, training data.
Soon | NTU: Which is, I only sell it to Fiverr.
Soon | NTU: I, I do not, put user… I think original value is 10, right?
Soon | NTU: Indeed.
Soon | NTU: Because 5 epoch already took me 10 minutes, so 10 will be 20 minutes, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so after we have trained the model, okay, so that is the, function, generateText. For us to do the text generation, okay, so basically, we're telling the model, oh, with this corpus that you have trained.
Soon | NTU: So, if you're given some text as a start.
Soon | NTU: How are you going to continue?
Soon | NTU: Okay, now the result you see, if you run it using our code, right, may or may not be, I would say…
Soon | NTU: you may end up like this, okay? So, I did not really train it, okay? So if you have time, try to train it with maybe 20 epoch and see whether you end up something like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is the… Okay, so this is, important to have this two, two devices.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so generate text. Likewise, we also have to be mindful that the…
Soon | NTU: Parameter, okay, that the model learned.
Soon | NTU: In the… In a device, okay, because subsequently, right, we're going to use it to do the,
Soon | NTU: generation, again. Now, because It potentially can have more than,
Soon | NTU: one, CUDA, or one GPU, okay? So, that is why you have this statement here, because we won't assume that there is only one CUDA with an index of zero, that means one CUDA, okay? So, this is actually to
Soon | NTU: make sure that our code runs regardless of whether there's a mixture. You can mix, using this CPU and GPU at the same time, okay? Because the parameter can be residing in different devices.
Soon | NTU: Potentially.
Soon | NTU: If you have more than one CUDA, Okay.
Soon | NTU: It can be resigned in CUDA Index 1.
Soon | NTU: If you have a second device, okay, in code them, I think there's only one, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now, the first statement here, right, is basically to,
Soon | NTU: We don't have to generate text, right? And then the model gives you numbers.
Soon | NTU: Okay, because your word embedding is numbered, but you want to…
Soon | NTU: We engineer and say, oh, if you give this number, right.
Soon | NTU: What is the word like in your vocabulary?
Soon | NTU: Okay, which is associated with this number.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this one, basically, I…
Soon | NTU: TOS is, integer to string.
Soon | NTU: Right? With a number, you're getting back the… Words from the vocabulary.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we just park it there, right?
Soon | NTU: And then… we have… the generate text with all these, parameters. Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: We have a long list of, tags or tokens to… for you.
Soon | NTU: which you're going to input it here. Okay, so this is our starting string.
Soon | NTU: And this is telling the generate text function
Soon | NTU: up to 100, token, okay, just generate, okay? So, you can go to this.
Soon | NTU: encounter. I didn't count, but… Probably east of about 100 lah, okay?
Soon | NTU: After the… the fox.
Soon | NTU: And you can count from agreed onwards, right?
Soon | NTU: So, if you look at this, right.
Soon | NTU: We also have taken into account the UNK, in case you're typing something which are not found in your vocab.
Soon | NTU: Like, we will be unknown.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so for INN, we also need to do some initialization of our hidden state.
Soon | NTU: Good.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then we copy the token.
Soon | NTU: We derived from the… Starting string.
Soon | NTU: Funny.
Soon | NTU: We just want to make a backup, okay, because, whatever…
Soon | NTU: words that… whatever token that the model generates, we want to append it to the original sentence, right? So that's why we want to
Soon | NTU: Back up this.
Soon | NTU: So, subsequent running of this statement will go through your the woods.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the selling stream to generate your text, okay?
Soon | NTU: It will stop until the 100 is reached.
Soon | NTU: So, basically, you are using the model to predict input. We have this hidden state. What is the output?
Soon | NTU: Okay? So, as you know, hidden…
Soon | NTU: The layer is one of the input, okay?
Soon | NTU: The previous layer, or the current,
Soon | NTU: For the current, output, right?
Soon | NTU: And then, this is, something very, interesting, right? So I try to explain this. Now, you know, temperature is one of the ways for us to
Soon | NTU: to tell our language model, you know, how creative You know, it can be…
Soon | NTU: Right? So, you know, if we have a temperature of less than 1, okay, so that will have,
Soon | NTU: A very deterministic… that means… If the wood appeal.
Soon | NTU: for this prediction, okay? If you run it with the same starting string, likely that the same word will appear, okay? So, that will mean your creativity is,
Soon | NTU: Not so much, right?
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Whereas, on the other hand, if you have a temperature which is more than 1, let's say…
Soon | NTU: 2 or 3 or 4, okay? So, that will give, a more randomness to the output
Soon | NTU: Okay, to the predicted, words, okay? So if you look at this, right, If temperature is small, Okay.
Soon | NTU: So… This one becomes a very big one.
Soon | NTU: Say temperature is 0.1.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this will be very huge number, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… Anything that is… Divided by a small number will be…
Soon | NTU: We have, let's say, 99.9%, this word is the word that you will choose.
Soon | NTU: For the next prediction, okay? So now, if your temperature is very…
Soon | NTU: big… let's say you have a 2 or 3, okay? So if you divide it by…
Soon | NTU: some number which is more than one, okay? So, the end result is…
Soon | NTU: All the numbers that you have, right? All the probability will be scale become closer.
Soon | NTU: Okay? It'll become closer. Closer means, if your word
Soon | NTU: that you have, used in the… with a temperature of 1, right? Let's say… Let's say, for example.
Soon | NTU: Do I have an example?
Soon | NTU: I say agreed, right? Agreed is up to the Fox, so that probably have some kind of a training data to
Soon | NTU: tell the model that, oh, the next word likely that it is, agreed, okay? So.
Soon | NTU: If you use a very… big temperature.
Soon | NTU: Okay. So, instead of… 90 over percent confident that, oh, the work is agreed, okay?
Soon | NTU: For everyone. So now, your percentage become lower.
Soon | NTU: Because this is a… Morning one.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the more the temperature, okay, the flatter your… your probabilities.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, and every word, right, like lead…
Soon | NTU: can be chosen for the next, prediction.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is, how it is, transforming this…
Soon | NTU: Okay, to make the model creative or not, deterministic, based on the temperature that you have,
Soon | NTU: put in here. Okay, so let's see whether it really works, because of the corpus that we have provided, you know. So, let's see whether it makes sense later. Okay, so we run a flop max.
Soon | NTU: to determine our probabilities, okay? Now we need to convert it back to our NumPy.
Soon | NTU: all the way.
Soon | NTU: From our tensor.
Soon | NTU: Dean.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and then you have a choice of this…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is, probabilities.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we got… Choosing one of the number.
Soon | NTU: Based on the… Okay, let me see what's this p-value.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so P is the probability associated with H.
Soon | NTU: So, we are using this probability to determine what number I should choose, okay?
Soon | NTU: for the…
Soon | NTU: the next, word that I have predicted, okay? So, you will not know what ID… what word it is based on this ID, so we work backwards to get the word that has an ID of,
Soon | NTU: Next ID.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and then we will save this.
Soon | NTU: to our… Okay, we'll take it to the starting sentence.
Soon | NTU: King.
Soon | NTU: So, for each iteration, we are going to predict the next word.
Soon | NTU: And then append it to the words, this is the… lease.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Of course, every prediction is a token, so we will have to A panel, a space.
Soon | NTU: Again, to separate each of the tokens.
Soon | NTU: Right, so we have, some three examples here with a different, value for the temperature, okay? So, you see.
Soon | NTU: If I have a temperature of 1, Right? So, it is…
Soon | NTU: Okay, main note… okay, it's considered quite deterministic. Okay, let's see…
Soon | NTU: Does it make sense? The quick brown fox agreed to signal to the substance of… okay, to me, it doesn't really make sense, right? I agree. But nevertheless, you can see, there's actually some tabs, right? The… the…
Soon | NTU: the texts are not of very high quality compared to the actual large language model that we have been using, right? But nevertheless, it can actually show us how we can actually build a
Soon | NTU: Ian model to do,
Soon | NTU: Prediction like this, using the ELP.
Hitesh shah: So, it will only use the word from the vocabulary, right? The 9,400 words, it will… the output will be only from the words which are there in the vocabulary.
Hitesh shah: Is it?
Hitesh shah: Or it can… it could also use some other English words.
Hitesh shah: Or just making a sense.
Soon | NTU: You can use another English word, of course.
Soon | NTU: You can use What, you know…
Hitesh shah: So the output that is coming right now is only from the vocabulary words, or it is also from the library?
Soon | NTU: is from the vocab, okay? Any word that is not in vocab will be unknown.
Soon | NTU: Okay. Sorry,
Soon | NTU: Off on the vocabulary.
Soon | NTU: Okay, because when you look at the, the… the something sentence, right?
Soon | NTU: The settings entered is, copy as is, without any, Modification by the model.
Soon | NTU: The model basically go to the,
Soon | NTU: Based on the width, right, that he has,
Soon | NTU: train, and then start to do prediction based on the corpus that you would train, okay? So the words that are here are all coming from the bootcamp.
Hitesh shah: So that's the 9,444 words which…
Soon | NTU: Yeah, 964. Correct, yeah.
Soon | NTU: Because, I do not think,
Soon | NTU: likely that it will use a word that is not in the vocab. Anyway, if you look at the logics, right.
Soon | NTU: Where is the vocab?
Soon | NTU: being used.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you see, we have, vocab here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so these are the input ID.
Soon | NTU: So, from the input ID,
Soon | NTU: Okay, so from the input ID, it's basically, anyway, we only have one hidden layer, right? So from the input ID,
Soon | NTU: You will make the prediction. Okay, so all this output will be from your… Okay.
Hitesh shah: Okay.
Soon | NTU: 0.01.
Soon | NTU: very, deterministic.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, deterministic, so if you have a word unknown, so all the way unknown.
Soon | NTU: For quite a while, right?
Soon | NTU: Many viewers, okay, so… I think this, kind of language model
Soon | NTU: Need to provide a lot of tunings, especially when we only use one hidden layer.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Lim Hung (Lanson): Why would that be the first time?
Soon | NTU: Huh? Sorry?
Lim Hung (Lanson): Why would there be a first unknown?
Soon | NTU: You mean this?
Lim Hung (Lanson): No, that makes, like… Like, how come there will be an unknown? That after the company, said the company.
Lim Hung (Lanson): S, then under.
Soon | NTU: Okay, unknown is not because of,
Soon | NTU: Unknown is not because of any Oh, okay, let me see…
Soon | NTU: Okay, as you can see, it is, using the vocabulary, right, To generate the next word.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the next predicted work based on whatever is in this…
Soon | NTU: sequence before the word that it's trying to predict, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: Unknown happened to be one of the words in the vocab.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… so it's quite misleading. Okay, why not… you try to remove the… the unknown and see how it works?
Soon | NTU: Because,
Soon | NTU: Where… because the unknown is inserted as a first item in the vocab, okay? So this one, even though it's unknown, but it's not…
Soon | NTU: Predicting a workdays.
Soon | NTU: Not in vocabulary, but instead, it is actually coming from the vocab. First word called unknown.
Soon | NTU: If I have a small t.
Soon | NTU: Right? Very decently sick, right? So once you have a Unknown all the way.
Soon | NTU: Rain.
Soon | NTU: So it doesn't give you a lot of, creative, prediction
Soon | NTU: Meaning, your, your predictor work is, very… Okay, at each location.
Soon | NTU: Great.
Soon | NTU: So, it's like… Someone keep repeating the same word, right?
Soon | NTU: Bye.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me see whether… Okay, so that's,
Soon | NTU: And the first part of the, Jupiter notebook, right? So we'll continue with this, the pre-trained model.
Soon | NTU: In the Part 2 and 3.
Soon | NTU: So he…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… Thank you so much for your attention.
germayne: Okay, do you guys need any break? Or let's continue.
germayne: And do you?
germayne: Why are you guys mowing?
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Only 5 minutes, I'll do it.
germayne: You guys good to go?
Easwaran Jayaraman: My direct fees.
germayne: 5 minutes, is it? Okay. Okay, let's come back on time, let's come back at 5.52.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yuma.
Chieh Cheng Lai: I asked a question in the chat, in the.
germayne: Beautiful.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Because I saw the example just now, you said F1, 0.01, then 0.2.
Chieh Cheng Lai: So, I remember you talking about if the temperature less than 1, the chances to predict the next word, the probability, become low. That's… that's the reason why, we…
Chieh Cheng Lai: in the… in… in the result, it shows that most of the words become an. Is that…
Chieh Cheng Lai: And the right to digits that…
germayne: Look, no, I just think, like, the mo- okay, I think that's… that's…
germayne: there's two… there's two reasons… there's two… there's two ways to think about the… the notebook example. I think number one, obviously, it's just a very…
germayne: It's just a very simple example. The architecture is not there, and…
germayne: the model is not meant to be good. A second takeaway is that normally, right, in… in text generation, there's actually a concept of, like, the…
germayne: the end of token. So basically, it's not supposed to be, like, predicting this unknown thing. So how it does in, let's say, the modern language model is that there's actually this start token, and there's this end token.
germayne: So it knows when to stop. It's not like… it's not like that. This is just a… this is just a toy example. The concept here is that the temperature, right, controls the creativity of the output.
germayne: If you set temperature to be zero, right, then the output is fixed.
germayne: It's always deterministic. I think that's the takeaway that you should take out. I think, why is it unknown? I just think it's just a bad model. Yeah, it's just a not good.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Also, this is not the… because I taught.
germayne: This is RNN, right? This is not… yeah.
germayne: Yeah, and it's just a very simple example, so it's not meant to be like, oh, you know, you train this and suddenly it's like… it's like…
germayne: GPT. If, let's say, you guys train something like GPT, let me know, I can invest in you, please let me know.
germayne: Okay? But I mean, it's just a toy example, you guys understand, right? It's just a very simple neural network with an RNN just to showcase the concept. But it's not meant to be like, oh my god, the result is good.
germayne: So typically, there's a lot more nuance that we didn't really go through, right? The way that the thing is tokenized is also not by words. There's other methods to tokenize it. And they usually have this, end of sentence, this EOS, start or sentence.
germayne: Right, then you know when to stop, right? Because otherwise, it can't keep going on forever, if you think about it.
germayne: You understand what I mean?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, so, so the, actually, the temperature over here.
Chieh Cheng Lai: doesn't… will bring us a fantastic, model. It's just, to underst… to… to try… try it out, fitting it in the next word, that's all.
germayne: The temperature is the same temperature as the LLM's temperature, because the output from the model is the same. What you are trying to predict is, you are predicting the probability of the vocab size, right? So given a sequence of words, what is the probability of the next vocab?
germayne: What temperature does is that it just allows you to control the selection of that token.
germayne: You understand what I mean?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Selections of the token.
germayne: Yes.
Chieh Cheng Lai: on the selection of the token. Can you explain this one clearly? I mean, I…
germayne: Because, because given a sequence of words, your output is, you're going to predict, you're going to predict
germayne: Team, let me, let me, let me, let me share my screen now.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay.
germayne: So what happens in the last layer, right? No matter what model that you guys are using. So what we taught just now is that you have some kind of sequence of data.
germayne: Again, I'm simplifying this.
germayne: you put into some kind of model. Today, we talked about RNN.
germayne: Later, I'll talk about RSTM.
germayne: current state-of-the-art users transformer, but it doesn't matter. It's just the block, it's just the block inside is different. Now.
germayne: your final output, right, even if it's a transformer, even if it's a large language model, the output is going to be something like you have, you have… you're going to predict the probability, so it's going to be something like…
germayne: Okay, let me think, let's say if you have one… one… one batch of data, you have
germayne: T sequence.
germayne: Sorry.
germayne: Let me, let me… Wait, where's my eraser?
germayne: Okay, so for example, right, what you have is you have a sequence, let's say you have X1, you have X2. You want to predict the next token.
germayne: So, what usually is an output here, right, is that you have the size of the vocab. So, let's say the vocab size is… Soon, what was the example that you used? 9000, is it?
Chieh Cheng Lai: No, 644.
germayne: 9644.
germayne: So basically, what you want to predict is you want to predict 9644 has a multi-class problem. So in your 9644, right, you just imagine there's a distribution.
germayne: There will be some token that has very high probability.
germayne: that high probability token will be the one that you select for this. The temperature basically controls the selection of the output. It's a multi-class problem, so everything here, the sum of, all the output here, right, sum of TI,
germayne: I equals to 1 equals to 9 6.
germayne: 44?
germayne: is actually equals to 1. Because I'm selecting a probability, right? Given all the words from previous… from previous output, what is the probability of the next word?
germayne: So the last layer in your neural network is just going to be 9644. 9644 hidden units.
germayne: Because I want to predict the probability of this.
germayne: Does that make sense?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Oh, okay, okay. Yeah, yeah, there's 9466 Lake, hidden layer.
germayne: Yeah, and that's because you want… that's because your vocab is 9644, in this example. Of course, in reality, the actual models, the vocab size is bigger.
germayne: And they don't express it as words. They use either byte pair encoding or some other methods. But in your simple example, if I'm able to express 9644, basically, imagine 9644 is just all the words. I am… I'm just simplifying it, I am a blah blah blah blah. There's 9644 of it.
germayne: Basically, what the model is trying to predict is, let's say out of the selection of these, I just predict what's the probability, right? If I want to predict, then, should be 0.8, then everything is, like, 0.00…
germayne: Et cetera, et cetera. Everything is just probability.
germayne: Okay? Does that make sense?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, then I will select the highest popularity, and we're putting it…
germayne: you don't always select the highest probability, because if you always select the highest probability, then it's always going to be fixed, right, your generation. So there are different mechanisms to choose. That is the technique to generate the text.
germayne: That one, I'll leave it… I think you can go and research yourself.
germayne: You'll be out of the class. But if you… you just imagine, if you always select the greedy, this greedy, right? If I always select the highest, that means that whenever I ask the same question, I'm always going to get the same output, correct?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yes, correct.
germayne: Yeah, but you don't want that, so there are different mechanisms to select.
germayne: To select the probability based on the vocab.
germayne: Okay, but it's not, it's not… we're not going to talk about it today, lah. I'll leave that.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay.
germayne: That's below.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, thank you.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, we, we, we got a lot. We still got a lot.
germayne: But I… I will just try my best.
germayne: Okay, I hope, I hope the… I hope the exercise actually made it easier to understand the RNN.
germayne: Hopefully. Okay? So, what we are going to do next is we are going to go next. We are going to move away from RNN, okay? And I want to just give you guys a takeaway of the intuition, okay? So, you notice, right, just now, I think we talked a bit about, we talked a bit about it.
germayne: For recurrent neural network, because the thing is sequential, it takes in each sequence output, and then we are just basically passing the hidden unit to the next, and then essentially, for backpropagation, is that we need to
germayne: Backpropagate so that we can update the weights.
germayne: Right? So backpropagation essentially is like that. So at the end, right, usually you have some kind of hidden unit, you've got some kind of loss. So what backpropagation does is that we're just passing this backwards. So you can see this is exactly what I said just now. You're just going back in time.
germayne: Right, you're just going backwards.
germayne: Okay? The only thing you need to take note is that the weight is the same here. Okay? And I want to give you guys an illustration why RNN is just not good. Okay? RNN is not meant to be good, it's meant to be a very old, it's old, it's already outdated.
germayne: Right, there's a problem with RNN, and I want to use math, so bear with me a bit, right? So, the next bridge here is why RNN is not good.
germayne: So, if you guys remember, on last week of Tuesday, we talked about updating the weight. So the… if you remember the formula, if whenever we want to update the weight, we take the… we take the weight from the previous instance.
germayne: We apply gradient descent.
germayne: Right, so we apply a learning rate, and then we apply the differential loss with respect to the width. We apply this, if you guys remember, we talk about this, right? So you want to make sure the W gets better and better with respect to minimizing the loss, because it's a parameter of the model.
germayne: The very big problem with RNN, right, because we are going backwards like that, and because it's the same, it's the same W, you basically can see, right, so this, this, this formula here is from the chain rule, if you remember here. Essentially, there's a chain rule that we will apply here, right? If you remember last week, we talked about chain rule.
germayne: So within this equation, chain rule, right, if you express these, right, so HT is basically the hidden unit generated at step T.
germayne: And in this, again, this is a very simple example, but at this step here, right, basically, we take the output previously, we multiply by the weight, and then we put some kind of nonlinear transformation. This is just a very simple example. Actual RNN doesn't look like that, but the illustration here is to just show that.
germayne: If I were to express these, right, the differential at time t.
germayne: Basically, it's just a multiplication. This thing here is just a multiplication, it's just a product. Here, right, this product, basically, I'm going to multiply this T number of times, and you can see that there's a W here. We bring the W out, so this W, I just bring it out, right? And you notice that W is raised to the power of t.
germayne: So W, right, is raised to a power of t, right, because we do it T times, we're doing a for loop.
germayne: Why is this a bad thing? The intuition to take away here is that the weight is always to the power of t. If your W is less than 1, what happens?
germayne: And a small number that is raised to a power, it means that the value will be very small, right?
germayne: Agreed?
germayne: Correct? So, if your W is less than 1, any number less than 1 raised to a power, the power, let's say in your sequence is 100,
germayne: 0.01 raised to power 100, you get something like 0.000, something that's very small. So what this means is that if the width updates here, right, this is the gradient that is being passed, if the gradient, right, is getting very small, what this means is that the gradient actually vanishes, which means that we're actually not updating anything. Your W is not getting updated.
germayne: And that's a bad thing, right? So basically, very hard to train the model. Essentially, you get a problem where the gradient is just not updated.
germayne: If W is very big, you get the exploding gradient, which means the gradient just exploded. Also very big. Also very bad, makes the training unstable.
germayne: So the learning here is that RNN is just not very good, because of this… this equation, because of this recurrence in the… in the width, right? And the formula here is that you just see W is raised to a power.
germayne: Right? And this is just the… this is one of the upstream gradients that is always being passed around to do chain rule in order to update the model, and it becomes very small. So if this is very small, basically, W is not getting updated at all.
germayne: So what people do is they actually create a new version, a better version of the RNN, which is called the long-short-Term Memory, okay? So instead of making it very simple, so if you look at this, it makes it like that, it looks like that now.
germayne: Okay? So essentially, they have a concept called the input gate, the output gate, the forget gate, blah blah blah, right? So now you realize that actually this is a bit more complicated, right? So what this means is that instead of, like, just doing very simple, linear layer, multiplied by a weight.
germayne: Right? Again, I'm, like, simplifying it. Actual RNN is, actual RNN, I think you can find… you can… wait on, let me…
germayne: Let me… Just show you guys.
germayne: Okay, the actual RNA looks something like that.
germayne: Right, you can see it's just… it's just something like that. But still relatively simple, right, with a 10H, which is a nonlinear layer, but you can see it's relatively simple. Okay?
germayne: But the idea here is that, why not we use LSTM, and actually LSTM, without getting into detail, LSTM actually
germayne: remove this W to the power of T, right? Instead of making it multiplicative, we actually make it additive, so that there's no… there's no concept of this vanishing gradient. Does LSTM completely remove vanishing gradient? Not really. Vanishing gradient still exists.
germayne: It's just that compared to RNN, the vanishing gradient is not as bad. So what's the… what's the takeaway? The takeaway here is that
germayne: If the vanishing gradient problem is actually improved, it means that it's actually easier to train the model, right? Maybe you don't have to train it
germayne: to… you know, it's easier to train, easier to get better, which is why I think in that example that you see, it's supposed to be lousy. Because RN, I don't think, is really that good, it's actually quite old already. And actually, LSTM, you can see here, is very, very complex, right? But I like to use… okay, so there's different kinds… I'm not going to talk about the group.
germayne: The GRU is just a simpler version of LSTM, but the LSTM is the main important thing. So actually, once LSTM came out, right, people straight away just replaced
germayne: RNN with LSTM. Most people just use LSTM because LSTM is better.
germayne: And the idea here is that you notice that it just has all these gates, so there's an input gate, there's an output gate, there's a forget gate.
germayne: I want to use the math equation to take some time to explain. I won't take too much time to talk about it.
germayne: Right? If you are a visual person, you can do it visually, right? But the idea here is that we basically introduce this cell, so basically, there's a cell here.
germayne: So the cell, right, just basically replaces the RNN block. So now the LEGO block, right, inside is very complex.
germayne: Right? But actually, it's not too bad, right? I'll walk you through again, right? Not very important. But again, the idea here is that you just want to pass the cell.
germayne: The cell state is actually the information that is extracted out in time step T. So let's say at time step 1,
germayne: you extracted certain information, you'll pass the cell information to the next sequence. So the next sequence will have information from the first sequence. And this should sound familiar, because this is exactly like what the RNN did, right?
germayne: every sequence, we take some stuff out, we just pass it to the next guy. So the next guy not only have contacts with the new data, it also has contacts from the previous sequence.
germayne: And because the gradient flows better.
germayne: The idea here is that it's able to retain information across the sequences, right?
germayne: So you can see, this whole thing, right, this, this, this, this whole journey, where the data flow in, multiplied by this, actually can be expressed as a very simple equation.
germayne: Okay, you guys might… you guys might feel like I'm just joking, right? Oh my god, why Jamie say this? It's actually very simple. But actually, right, if you think about it, it's actually…
germayne: It's just the same thing. You look at here, it's just W multiplied by XT plus buyers. This is similar to what we saw in the feed-forward. It's just that now they created multiple elements here, but don't need to memorize this. What I want to do is I just want to walk you through the intuition, right, the takeaway from here.
germayne: So the… the idea is at every time step we compute the input gate, the forget gate, the… the… the… the…
germayne: the GT, output gate, cell, and then the hidden. What I want you to focus on is actually looking at the cell state, this one. This is the important one, because this one is the one where we are actually passing information from each time step, from time step 1, we pass to 2, we pass to 3. Actually, bulk of the information comes from this CT.
germayne: This CT, right, from an equation perspective, got 4 parts. FT,
germayne: CT-1 is the previous time step.
germayne: IT is the input, input for that time step, and GT is just another element that I'll talk about later. So if you think about it, right, forget about the equation, just focus on this. There's just 4 things that we want to do here. Forget it.
germayne: What exactly is ForgetGate doing?
germayne: ForgetGate, basically, is just training the model to identify what information that I'm passing previously, right?
germayne: whether it's important or not. So imagine, now you're at time step 3.
germayne: At time step 3, at C3, you're trying to generate C3, so what will you get? You will get C2, which is the cell that actually was generated previously, and now is giving to you.
germayne: What forgetGate does is that if you look at this equation, right, if forget gate is 0, what happens?
germayne: Can I guys ask you, if FT… if I set FT to be 0, What does it mean?
Zac Ang: Zero.
germayne: It means I forget about this guy, right?
germayne: Right? I forget about the thing that was passed previously. So actually, what the, what the intuition here is that actually the forget gate, right, is just learning whether to keep the information for this step or not.
germayne: Okay, I'll repeat again. So what the FT is learning, right, from this equation, this one, I'm just putting it here, this FT is actually going to be between 0 and 1, and if you think about it, right, the model is actually giving this
germayne: this is like a gatekeeper. This gatekeeper is basically controlling how much of an information shall I retain from the previous cell.
germayne: If the previous cell is useless, then I'm just going to put 0 lah, right? The model will do it for you. And the idea here is that this controls how much of the previous cell you need to know. If, let's say, the previous cell is very important, then I'll just put a 1 lah, right? The model will just put a 1, the model will automatically learn it.
germayne: So that's actually for the first part of the sale, right? We already talked about the first part already,
germayne: So done already, right, we talked about the first part. Now I'll talk about the second part, this one.
germayne: Right, the IT and the GT.
germayne: GT, right, is basically the… it's like a candidate update lah. So basically, right, if you guys remember, at every time step, at every time step T, right, you get two things.
germayne: You get information that is learned from the model previously, and you get new, fresh output at this time step.
germayne: So this GT is basically, like, another gate, another gatekeeper that controls, like, okay, how much of the input that you are giving me is relevant, right? If it's relevant, then here it will be high. If it's not relevant, again, if this is zero, this whole thing gets canceled out.
germayne: So actually, if you look at what the intuition, it's actually not too bad, right? The intuition.
germayne: And then the final one is the input. This is basically the input.
germayne: that, based on the existing data, what are the data that is important, right? So, you can just see, right, this whole complex cell is just basically having a control system where they're just deciding what information to keep, what information to throw, before I generate and pass on to the next guy. That's it.
germayne: Right? Everything else is the same. The HT is exactly the same that you saw. There's going to be a hidden unit that is learned and outputted every T, right? Because for every block.
germayne: For every LSTM block, right, you will get a hidden unit, HT.
germayne: Right? And then this one, you also get HT. Exactly the same as the one that you guys saw, nothing changes. And then, again, takeaway here is, again, it's like a for loop, because it's the same thing, the only thing that we change is that we make the inside of the cell more complex.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: All good, right. So actually, that's LSTM. Lstm, obviously, for a long period of time, was very good, but the drawback of LSTM still remains the same. You need to process the data sequentially, because the architecture looks the same, it looks like that.
germayne: Right? It looks like that, nothing changes. Only we make the whole equation we squeeze into this cell. But what this means is that it needs a for loop.
germayne: And we need to loop this one by one. So that's the… that's the big bottleneck.
germayne: Right, yeah, until… until… okay, so I'm going to move on to Transformers. So, Transformer is basically the newest thing.
germayne: Not that new lah, by the way, but it's just new because it's the best today, and it solves a lot of problems that LSTM and RNN faced.
germayne: Okay? So, I want to give you guys some warning, right? This will, of course, be hard.
germayne: Okay, but again, this is actually the latest things today.
germayne: So, I… I will try my best, okay, to paint the story and to make it as easy as possible, but just understand this is the latest, latest, latest thing, so if you understand this, then basically you sort of, like.
germayne: You know, every, every, every material historically that you know will just
germayne: propagate to this. So the… the thing here I want to show you guys is that in the original Transformer paper when they released, they actually released, like, that… this encoder, which is the first half of the square, and the decoder is the second half of the square.
germayne: The story here is because, right, if you… and you need to follow the story. The story is because
germayne: back then, right, whatever that people use for RNN and LSTM is actually mostly used in this, translation task. So usually what people do is they have this thing called sequence-to-sequence.
germayne: It's, again, outdated, really, but back then, they had this sequence-to-sequence model, which actually handles translation. And what people do is that in translation, they actually created this encoder-decoder architecture. Which is why I think when Transformer came out, they decided to do this encoder-decoder architecture.
germayne: But then, if you ask me, right, we have actually moved on from this encoder-decoder, and you will see why later, okay? Decoder, obviously, is the… the… we will talk about it later, but let's just start with this whole architecture first, okay? So transformer, right, if you think about it.
germayne: It's built to handle sequential data, but the mechanism is actually very different than LSTM and RNN. And usually when people talk about transformer, they're going to explain two things, two important things, okay?
germayne: And this is just what I showed lah. So basically, this is the old architecture on the LSTM, right? And I want to draw parallel to you guys, because you'll notice it's the same thing, right? It's encoder-decoder, the inside changed, but architecturally, it's the same.
germayne: And you notice that this is actually used in sequence-to-sequence, where people use it for machine translation, so you put in some English text, and then you expected another translation. And notice there's some token here, this SOS and AOS is basically the end of sentence and the start of sentence, okay? Which is, normally, we don't hand them with the unknown, usually there's a token for this.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So I want to just draw parallel. And then, for encoder-decoder, right, this architecture mostly is used in machine translation, right? But now, right, when people start to realize that actually you don't really need encoder-decoder, you just, you know, break them up separately.
germayne: Everything that is text generation, we call it decoder, okay? So if you always hear me say, like, oh, it's just decoding, decoder, it's because all the language models today, all the LLM, they are all based on the decoder architecture.
germayne: Encoder is still very important, because all the BERT-based models is still using encoder, okay? Now, are these terms new? Not really. Encoder-decoder is used in machine translation. Decoder is because
germayne: in the… in the translation task, your decoding is basically a recurring thing again. You put in the… the first output that you generate is going to be fed back into the model to generate the second output.
germayne: The two outputs that you generate is going to recursively put back, so that's why it's like a decoding task. That's why it's called decoder. Encoder, just like the term suggested, I'm sure you guys already know by this. Given some kind of input data X, I want to represent this in some high dimension. That's an encoding task.
germayne: We talk about this again in computer vision, where you put in an image.
germayne: I don't know, use CNN, use visual transformer, we're just going to output them into some kind of high dimension. That is an encoding. Encoding task, and resulting of the output usually is some kind of embedding. Okay? So you notice I'm using consistent terms.
germayne: But I'm just trying to illustrate here that we already moved on to separating the decoder and coder, okay?
germayne: Now, when people talk about transformer, there's only two important things you need to take away, okay, when people talk about transformer. Two concepts on Transformer that is super important. One is the position.
germayne: One is the attention.
germayne: Okay? If you can master these two, then, to some extent, you understand what Transformer does. So the beauty of Transformer is the position encoding and the multi-hit attention. Okay? And…
germayne: At a very high level, transformers actually don't need us to put in the data one by one, we don't need to do it like LSTM.
germayne: Right, if you guys remember LSTM, I need to put X1, X2, X3, one by one, right? Beauty of transformer is you don't need to do that one by one, you put everything together all at once.
germayne: So, obviously, this… Makes it so scalable, right?
germayne: And this is actually due to the fact of the position.
germayne: Because you need to know what the position is, right? If I'm putting everything at once, the position still matter. Where the sequence of the word matters, agreed?
germayne: the position of the token matters and affects the context. And attention, we're going to talk about it later. Okay, so I'm going to just go through the first one.
germayne: So in the original paper, you guys can go back and explore this, I'm not going to take too much time, the idea is that you can actually encode the position into some kind of
germayne: dimension which captures the position of the input. And they actually used this… this is the old method also lah, actually, we also, you know, the newer architecture also has moved on already. This was, I think, introduced in the first paper. I can't really remember, I think it's a separate paper. But basically, we can use the sinusoidal, which is basically the sine cosine wave.
germayne: And basically what we can do is, using this function, if you look at the function here.
germayne: we can actually use this function to encode the position of the tokens. And what will happen is that you can go back and play with this, but essentially, using this function, I can generate a D dimension, the dimension will affect the function, you can see the formula here, there's a D.
germayne: The dimension, again, is defined by you. If I define dimension to be 50, what will happen is that I'm able to encode
germayne: For N and N by T token, I'll get an N by T positional vector.
germayne: Okay? And this is very important because it captures information about the position of each tokens, right? And we generate them
germayne: for all T number of tokens. And what we do is, later on, we'll just use this, and we're going to add it to our embedding output. So if you guys remember, there's an embedding output that you generated, right, just now, previously. The embedding is going to be, again, this.
germayne: And the embedding, there's an embedding here, if you guys remember. If your vocab is V, V number of vocab, and D in your embedding layer, you're going to get this output. Notice these two shapes is exactly the same, so what you do is you just add them together.
germayne: Right? And why you do that is because you want to capture the encoding, the context of where the information or the token is, right, at which position. You're going to capture it, and you're going to add it into the embedding vector. So what this means is that, from a model perspective.
germayne: I do not need to sequentially put in the inputs one by one, but yet the model knows the position of the tokens. So that's actually what the position encoding does.
germayne: Of course, this is no longer relevant. People have found, a better mechanism, but I'll talk about it later, okay? So for now, this is position encoding. So this is the first ingredient.
germayne: Now, I'm going to talk about the second ingredient. Second ingredient is this thing called self-attention.
germayne: Okay? So, I'm going to try my best to give you the illustration. Obviously, I'm not the one that created this. This guy, Jay, he's a fantastic guy. I added his blog post. His blog post is amazing, right? Back then, when I wrote the transformer from scratch, I also used his blog. So…
germayne: the idea here is, right, let's just, like, just look at, let's look at this sentence. So, if you look at this sentence, a robot must obey the orders given it by human beings
germayne: Except where such orders would conflict with the first law.
germayne: If you look at this example, has a human being
germayne: Can you guys tell me what is the EAT?
germayne: Who, who is the EAT referring to?
Zac Ang: Robot.
germayne: Exactly, so the it is actually on the robot.
germayne: Such orders. What are such… what is a such order? Who gave the order? The human, right? The human gave the order, right?
germayne: would conflict with the first law. Obviously, the first law is not mentioned here, but the idea here is that you notice word context is actually determined by that, for a given word, let's say eat, right? The context is actually captured in robot. Because as a human being, we know, right, when we say eat, we are actually referring to the robot.
germayne: So what attention is actually trying to solve is that actually for words, right, if I'm able to know
germayne: For it, for example, Which word preceding it, as well as after it.
germayne: is it related to it? Would be very helpful for me to understand linguistic, or the context of the sentence. Anybody disagree with this?
germayne: So the statement here that I'm claiming is that for any sentences that we are doing.
germayne: usually the context of it, right, is that there's some kind of relation to the word with respect to another word in that same sentence. As human beings, we obviously can derive that easily, but from a machine perspective, they don't… they don't know.
germayne: And what you want to do is you want to say that, okay, the it seems to be referring to robot, right? Human beings, such orders. Orders is actually given by a human being.
germayne: And this basically forms the context of the sentence, because otherwise the sentence is meaningless, right?
germayne: So, that's the first claim that I'm doing. Anybody here disagree with this claim? That, in a sentence.
germayne: the context actually somehow matters based on certain words, and there's some relation between each of the words. And the words might not happen sequentially. You look at it, robot is actually so far away. By the time it comes to it, right, actually we are referring to robot, but it's actually, I don't know what sequence already.
germayne: Correct? So it's actually not really sequential.
germayne: I want to give a pause here first.
germayne: Anybody disagree? Anybody wants to discuss? Because if you don't… if you don't finish… if you don't understand this, it will be very complex later on. Any question? All of you agree with me, with this statement?
germayne: So, so far, can agree, right?
germayne: Agree, okay. So once you believe this, right, so the premise here is that we are saying, the claim that I'm claiming is that for sentence meaning, actually, I want to know the relation between the words that precede it, as well as the word after it, whether what is the relation to it. So let's just use an example of it.
germayne: Because here we know that it actually refers to robot.
germayne: So the idea of Transformer is you're going to do what is called self-attention, which means for every word, I'm going to find the relation with respect to it. So I'm going to do…
germayne: versus everything, robot versus everything, and it versus everything. So I'm going to show you an example. So, in this example, right, the hand-wavy analogy here, without going through the math, is that imagine it has a vector. So this vector is the one that you calculated.
germayne: If you guys remember from the embedding.
germayne: So this vector, right, is it, but I want to know which word actually has the meaning with respect to it. So the analogy given here is just imagine you want to find… you got a sticky pad. Just imagine, in the office, you got a sticky pad. Sticky pad here says it.
germayne: Each of the file in the cabinet is actually a word in the sentence, so you can see a robot must obey. Of course, got a lot more, but we are just showing the example here. And the idea here is that you want to find a query, which is the it, right? You want to find the… you want to find the folder that is the most relevant to it.
germayne: You know, obviously, robot is going to be the most relevant, because the it refers to the robot, correct?
germayne: And we're going to let the algorithm learn this by itself, but the idea here is that I want to check against each of the folder, and I want to see which folder is actually the most relevant to the query.
germayne: Oops, sorry.
germayne: Okay? So, in this example, each folder represents a word that you'll need to compare with, right, the folder in the cabinet.
germayne: The cabinet actually has a key.
germayne: The key is basically the reference that we need to match it with.
germayne: Right? The value is basically the content of the… the word.
germayne: Okay? So the idea here is that, intuitively, in this sentence, I know it refers to robot.
germayne: So basically, hey, I must, I must know that actually robot and, robot, robot actually is the one that has a lot of context.
germayne: With respect to it. The rest maybe doesn't really matter. So in this case, right, I know that this sticky pad actually belongs to this, and belongs to this, correct? So what I'm trying to tell you here is that
germayne: in… A very easy-to-explain term, 50% of robot and 30% of, actually…
germayne: Give me context for the word eat.
germayne: While the rest is actually very small. So, if I were to compare everything, right, all of the folder, everything will be 100% the weightage. But I'm saying that 50% of the context actually lies with robot. 30% of the context lies with it. The remaining 80% is just between all the other words.
germayne: So what I'm trying to do here is that, from a file cabinet perspective, I'm saying that the robot end is actually very important. Agreed? Agreed so far, right? Can follow, right? Now.
germayne: the… the key here, right, is that the key, the KR, here is the KR, this is K, this is Q,
germayne: Q is the one that we are comparing, K is the… the…
germayne: You know, which one is important?
germayne: No.
germayne: what is the content of the robot? The content actually lies with the value. Because if you found the thing that you want to find in the folder, the folder is not important, correct? You know, you locate the folder already, the folder is, like, you know, in the drawer, you're able to find the, you know, this… I don't really know what you call this thing, you know this thing?
germayne: You know, in a typical show, you have this thing that's protruding, so you are finding it, right? But this thing is not important. You still need to open up the folder to look at the value, because the value is the content, correct?
germayne: So what is actually attention?
germayne: Attention, essentially, is In the case of it, so basically, again, this queue is the it.
germayne: I'm basically saying that all of the words, right, must have some kind of weight. I'm just trying to find the weight, and you know that, you see, robot is very big, 50% of it.
germayne: It's actually 30%. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to take a multiplication between the key and the value.
germayne: Right? So because this tells me if 50% of robot is important, right, I'm going to take 50% of the content of robot, so I'm going to take 50% multiplied by this.
germayne: So you can see, so this becomes like that. Then, if the weight is very small, right, then the content will be very small. You can see, right? So basically, what I want to do is, I want to find some kind of linear combination of all the other words with respect to the
germayne: what it…
germayne: So basically, what I'm trying to do here is that I'm expressing it by saying that, okay, a robot…
germayne: with its file content, and content is the value here, I'm saying that actually this tool is 80% of the context that each should care, while it's combined with other, other, other words, which is, like, small percentage. So what I basically do is I take the score, which is from K,
germayne: I multiply by V, this is Q,
germayne: V multiplied by K, I basically get these, right? And what I do is I basically sum them up. I add all of them, because it's a linear combination, I'm going to add all of them.
germayne: And when I add all of them, I basically get one output here.
germayne: And this output now, what does it represent? It represents, out of all the whole sentence, Right? It represents…
germayne: The context of the sentence with respect to it.
germayne: This is only for one word, by the way, this is only for one word.
germayne: So what this means is that you realize, this pink color tree vector.
germayne: It's actually heavily weighted from a robot. Agreed?
germayne: Agree with me, right? Because when I sum them up.
germayne: 80% of the content actually came from a robot. So, actually, you can think of it, right, this pink thing represents a representation of the sentence where the important words already represented it in the vector.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So that's attention. And what we're gonna do? We're gonna do it for every word.
germayne: Because we do it for every word, right? So now I only do it for one word.
germayne: And it's called self-attention because you do it for one word, but now you do it for all the words. So every word will have its own representation, its own idea of which word is more important with respect to it. So actually, if you think about it, it's quite simple, right? Agree, right? The analogy.
germayne: Okay, what is difficult is little when you do the math, but we're not doing the math.
germayne: The idea here is that in language models, they actually do this thing called multi-headed self-attention. So, you do it for all of the word, every word you do it, right? So you have n tokens, sorry, you have N dataset, you have T tokens. So basically, you will generate
germayne: all of it, for n of it, for T of it, n times t, you'll do all of it. And usually what people do is they created multiple self-attention. So not just one attention, you created, like, so in this example, you can create… so in here, you got one…
germayne: 2…
germayne: And 3. So basically, you can create multiple. And the idea here is you just want to have parallel attentions that is being learned, right? And then you just combine all of them into here.
germayne: And basically, that's a secret ingredient for attention, and basically, it just works very well.
germayne: I gave the thing here. Whatever I describe here is written verbally by Jay. The Jalam, Jalama, J, alama, right? Basically, fantastic, fantastic illustration. Okay? That's where I understood it. Fantastic. I really, really highly recommend it. Okay? Of course, this is still in a hand-wavy way.
germayne: If you want to go one step further, you can write the transformer from scratch, even best, even better, then you'll understand the math.
germayne: But the idea is that we are just doing this.
germayne: Actually, it's quite, quite simple, right, if you think about it. I stop here first.
germayne: Anybody got any questions, or actually, so far, it makes sense. Very simple, from an intuition perspective.
germayne: And… and by now, right, at 9.26, you should realize that Transformer basically already solved the problem that we have with the sequence data.
germayne: Firstly, we don't really need the data to be put in sequence sequentially, but yet, somehow, we can capture the importance of the sequence in front and behind of the sequence, from each sequence itself.
germayne: Alright, all good, right?
germayne: Easy, right? Easy? I did my best.
Zac Ang: Sorry, can I ask what you do with the sum, then? You take the K and the V, you multiply it, and then you sum it up. Then what's next?
germayne: What is next issue?
germayne: So basically, you'll put everything, you'll put into a fit-forward, basically, you'll learn some representation.
germayne: Of each of the tokens. Because whatever that you sum up already contains information, right?
germayne: Right? You're, you're, you're, you're just collecting information
germayne: with respect to the token, so now you have… you are attending it to it already. So basically, now you have a weighted. And the model… obviously, the model will automatically learn the… the…
germayne: In here.
germayne: The weights, actually, are the ones in W, Q, and V. QKV, actually. These are all the weights that will be learned.
germayne: So this actually will get better and better once you backpropagate.
germayne: Okay?
Zac Ang: So, so this is, like, the hidden layers, this is…
germayne: Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah, these are the weights, yeah, these are the weights. These are the weights that eventually the value vector would be updated, the query vector will be updated, the key will also be updated.
germayne: So actually, if you think about it, it's just summing up important information. And all this important information, if you look at the whole architecture, right, basically what we talk about is, we need to talk about this, but there's this adding, and then here you want to learn more stuff as well, right? You want to project them to another hidden dimension, you put into a fit-forward layer.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay.
germayne: So fantastic, you guys really understand attention. So if you go into any interview, I think if you can explain this right, I would say you're pretty good. Then you should be able to explain attention. Right? That's a GS radiR, by the way. Actually, I… I believe this is really 90% of it already, right? So I'll just give you extra materials to read.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Now, I want to go back to a bit of what we talked about. So, this is just extra material. Obviously, this is the latest
germayne: positional encoding, so some of the latest models. Again, I don't really know the word latest by now. I don't dare to say latest, because
germayne: Actually, the rotary positional embeddings was quite popular. I believe it's still relevant today, but it is an upgrade from the old method. But I don't want to go… I don't want to go through too much here.
germayne: But the idea here is that they actually apply a different method to capture positional… to capture the positional information, and…
germayne: I added this extra slide here, you can go and read. Basically, they actually apply the positional encoding, they apply it before the attention layer.
germayne: Okay? And why is it very popular is that it's actually proven to be very good for extrapolating longer sequences. So if you guys realize, in large language models today, right, a lot of the new models actually come out with very huge context window. I think in the past, it used to be
germayne: 250K tokens, correct? Now can go up to a million. So the idea is that, actually, rotary positional embeddings plays a part in generalizing to very long sequences.
germayne: Okay, I'll stop here so far. So actually, we have already finished, talking about the internals of this.
germayne: Okay? We have talked about the internals of this.
germayne: And this… now I want to talk about the whole thing here from an encoder perspective.
germayne: But before I move on, any questions for me?
germayne: Interesting, right?
Zac Ang: Sorry, can I ask, we learned about the cosine similarity thing, then, now you talk about the position, the two different types of position, like, it's the same concept, right?
germayne: Not really, lah, not really. I think you treat them as separate. I think the… the… the cosine similarity is if I have two embedding space, right, how do I know whether they are close to each other? This… this positional… positional encoding is just…
germayne: A different mechanism to capture the position
germayne: In terms of a sequence of data, it's not really the same, yeah.
Zac Ang: Okay.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so let's continue on. Okay, so I, I already gave you… oh, sorry.
germayne: Okay, so yeah, you can watch yourself. So I… I talked a bit about the internal… internal portion of the… of the transformer, but we want to talk about this.
germayne: this one now. So if you recall, right, I mentioned that actually nowadays, we no longer use encoder-decoder, we just basically, look at the architecture separately. So one is encoder, one is decoder, okay? So I'm going to talk about BERT as an encoder. So basically, what is encoding is basically the same thing.
germayne: we basically… okay, so I'll just talk a bit about the history lah. So Bird actually came from Google, and actually, my team actually started using Bird in 2019 already. We actually… when they first released Bird, we are… we started using it already, and the performance is insanely good.
germayne: So the idea here is that Google actually used BERT to do, I think, mass language modeling. Basically, they were trying to predict and fill in the gaps. But you can do transfer learning by taking the model and then apply it to whatever task you have.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So you can see, basically, this is whatever that we talk about, the whole… this is the LEGO block that we talk about, the multi-attention head, the one that we talk about learning the context. So essentially, BERT just basically stacks all of these encoder blocks to learn the representation of the text data. And what is the objective?
germayne: The objective is given n by t sequence.
germayne: I want to learn a representation N by T by D.
germayne: Not very different, right? It's exactly the same. Exactly the same as LSTM, exactly the same as… but the only… the only difference is that this representation that's learned is very powerful. It's fantastic, right? Good performance.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: there are some nuances here, not gonna go into the detail, but typically, the BERT model, essentially, you can see here a couple of information here, right? They basically add the positional embeddings with the token embedding, I think I mentioned this already.
germayne: And essentially, it takes in all the sequence simultaneously, right? Attention model, you can put in all at once, it will calculate the self-attention.
germayne: And once you get the self-attention, it will come up with the hidden representation, or each of it. And typically, people like to use the CLS, right, because it represents the entire thing.
germayne: So if you relate this to RNN, it's actually very similar, right? For certain cases where we want to take one hidden unit to represent the whole thing, we just take the one at the end, HT, if you guys remember. But for BERT, the convention is they like to use the CLS to represent the entire thing, right? So if you want to do many-to-many, then you use the entire thing.
germayne: Right, if you want to do many to one, then you take the CLS. So, similar concept to RNN.
germayne: Okay, so BERT actually very, very popular, because…
germayne: You know, now that we have people that pre-trained on millions of data, you don't have to do from scratch, so actually very similar to computer vision right now.
germayne: You take the bird, you throw away the fully connected layer, because Google used this for much language modeling, you don't need that, and then you put your own fully connected layer, and you can do text classification, you can do Q&A, you can do name-entity recognition, you can do sentiment analysis.
germayne: even without fine-tuning the model, the performance usually at the start is fantastic, okay? That's why it's so powerful, and that is why NLP actually has shifted, okay? So I'm telling you what the industry is doing. In practice, people do fine-tune their data set by using their own fully connected layer, and they do update the BERT model, okay?
germayne: Okay, this one is just, no longer very relevant also. Albert, I think, is a small one, but there's, like, a deeper tar, there's actually a lot of new models now. So if you're interested, you can actually just go and find out what are the latest ones that people are using, but conceptually, they are similar, okay?
germayne: Okay, so I think… I think we will… we will go through with one example, right? And you'll realize that from a code perspective, fun fact, these are all just one line. It's just one line of code, you just import one line. It's just one single line. You don't even need to actually care about the attention, that's what makes it very easy for application.
germayne: You only care about attention if, let's say, you are trying to build your own from scratch, okay? If, let's say, you have some use cases.
germayne: Okay, so I'll hand it over to,
germayne: soon, but soon, can you give me, 10 minutes, if possible, at the end? You try your best, but I think I need 10 minutes to wrap up.
Soon | NTU: Okay, will do.
germayne: Yeah, okay.
Soon | NTU: 10 minutes for the Slido, what?
germayne: No, 10 minutes for me to wrap up. 10 minutes for me to wrap up, yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay, okay, we'll do…
germayne: I still have the decoder part, I think. Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me share, sorry.
Soon | NTU: To look for the…
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me go back.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so just now we stop at this,
Soon | NTU: section here to show how we can actually use this trained IN model to do the, prediction.
Soon | NTU: Okay, generating text like this, alright? So the next, part… Part 2 is about the… Boot.
Soon | NTU: Okay, sorry, I had to go to… okay.
Soon | NTU: So, in this, notebook, right, is… basically, we are showing, two things, right? First is, sentiment analysis, and then secondly, it's on the, name-entity, recognition. Okay, so let me quickly go through this, okay? So, to do that, we need to install…
Soon | NTU: the transformer library.
Soon | NTU: Let me see where… okay, so this is the…
Soon | NTU: first, could sell for this book section, okay? So, we need to be specific about the type of library that we need to
Soon | NTU: installed, because transformer also have,
Soon | NTU: TensorFlow-related library, which we do not need it in our notebook.
Soon | NTU: Right? So, now, this… Data set, load dataset, again, is, a way this…
Soon | NTU: the PyTalk, or I would say the Hugging Face way of, loading, for you to specify, what library you need for… before you load your data set. Okay, so I think there is some, prompt that you may need to
Soon | NTU: Confirm.
Soon | NTU: Okay, I think it will stop to prompt you for a why or a no, okay, because this,
Soon | NTU: Data will come in with a lot of,
Soon | NTU: train data, test data, from the IMDB, which is a movie, dataset. If you can still recall when we used it, is it in the
Soon | NTU: 2.8.
Soon | NTU: processing, right? We use the AMDB, okay? So, basically, it contains,
Soon | NTU: A lot of review by the, you know.
Soon | NTU: Those, people who watch the movies, okay? And then they gave a lot of,
Soon | NTU: command, right, feedback, right? So, this is a very good data set for us to do the sentiment analysis, right? So, we have the text, just a dictionary of,
Soon | NTU: two elements, right? Text, this is the review, and then labor will indicate zero for
Soon | NTU: I think 0 for negative sentiment, 1 for positive sentiment, okay? So, this is how…
Soon | NTU: the… we load, the bird-related library, King.
Soon | NTU: For us to do our, fine-tuning, customization, okay.
Soon | NTU: Because, for… to customize this support, we… we have, the other… Boom.
Soon | NTU: classes that we can use. Okay, so in this case, we used a bird for sequence classification, right? For sentiment analysis. I think for the other use cases.
Soon | NTU: NER, name entity recognition, I think there is, a different kind of, class that you need to import, right? So, these are the standard, training
Soon | NTU: Function that we, can leverage to train the
Soon | NTU: Leverage on this, pre-trained model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that will take care of a lot of things, rather than we are going to write it manually in terms of the batching, how we are going to fine-tune the weight, how fast.
Soon | NTU: the learning rate, and so on. Okay, so all these things are encapsulated for you. And, of course, to use a pre-trained model, okay, we definitely would need to have a GPU,
Soon | NTU: available, okay? So now, for pre-trained model, both come with, a different, variance. Okay, so in this case, we
Soon | NTU: have chosen the bird-based Are the case.
Soon | NTU: So, this is basically… will convert all your token into lowercase.
Soon | NTU: Sorry, this un case is,
Soon | NTU: lowercase everything, right? So, if you can counter a token like Apple, it'll be converted to all lowercase like this, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, of course, there are other, variations, you know, case, keeping all, uppercase, and so on, okay? So you can find out the different variants of birth, okay, from the ChatGPTA, okay?
Soon | NTU: Okay, now, we need to create one, depending on the corpus that we use, since we are using the IMVP, right? So we will have to, specify
Soon | NTU: Maximum length of 128, okay? So, depends on the data set, okay? So, this basically is…
Soon | NTU: Doing a lot of padding, because some review may be short, some review may be long, but we just want to standardize it, choose a standard length.
Soon | NTU: of…
Soon | NTU: 128, anything that's smaller than that, we chop it, right? Trulcation through. Anything that is shorter than 1 to 8, we pair it with some,
Soon | NTU: maybe spaces, okay? So, this is how the thing… okay, now this convert label is for us to patch the label column, right? In case the…
Soon | NTU: number in the label column have a 0, 1, 2, okay? So, in this case, anything that is 1 is considered positive sentiment. Anything that is not 1 is considered
Soon | NTU: negative sentiment, including a value of 2, okay? I have not checked the dataset. I'm not sure whether there's a value of 2 in the IMDB dataset, okay? So you can find it out.
Soon | NTU: So, this is how we create that, specific classification. We call it the headline. Okay, we are going to override it, the default headache comes with the bird.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, okay, so this is how…
Soon | NTU: We specify our own head, because we're going to predict,
Soon | NTU: it's a logistic, so-called projection, either 0 or 1, right? Now, you will see something like this because, once you text some, alien hit to the existing weight, okay, so you will have something like this, right?
Soon | NTU: it just… nothing alarming about the status, okay? Just to tell you that, oh, because you will need to retain the weight, existing weight, but only the head portion you need to retrain, okay? And then we need to specify the training.
Soon | NTU: argument. I've actually gone through some of this, detail, okay, so… This is, very important.
Soon | NTU: Really, because I think For pre-trained model, we try not to start off with, you know.
Soon | NTU: to adjust the widths drastically, because the default is width 0.0005, okay? So, it's still considered quite huge if the bird, language model is, being used for your fine-tuning, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: This is, more for regularization, okay? So, and then, we will start off with our training.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: And then, this training… Is, thinks how much you think?
Soon | NTU: It took me about 11 minutes moving. So you can try it out to have No, for…
Soon | NTU: training using the pre-trained model, right? So, typically, we just do not need to have,
Soon | NTU: very… too many epochs. One epoch should be sufficient, right? Because, most of the weight, we are trying to reuse the weight that come with the bird, yeah.
Soon | NTU: So we evaluate the training.
Soon | NTU: Performance.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: And then… We will… start to build our tokenizer, again, because, When we do the,
Soon | NTU: prediction, right? We first need to tokenize, our input, right?
Soon | NTU: Text.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And then we… Of course, some of the parameters are quite important, yeah.
Soon | NTU: If you don't specify PyTorch, Tensor, by default, it is, a list of, Python list of, values, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: And then, here we are.
Soon | NTU: We predict. So this is a text that we have, provided, and then
Soon | NTU: Based on whatever we have trained the corpus, whatever data that we have, okay, we have already successfully
Soon | NTU: Customize, okay, our… Bird model, okay, to predict the sentiment of this statement.
Soon | NTU: We are no longer telling it to do generating something or doing some other,
Soon | NTU: I think there are a few use cases, okay? So, in this case, it will give you a… either a 0 or 1, 1 for positive, and…
Soon | NTU: 0 for negative, okay? So, if you try to give, a center which is, a bit out of,
Soon | NTU: context, right? Not watching the movie, but something about the pain, then… It will be…
Soon | NTU: It may be confused, huh?
Soon | NTU: Anyway… Right.
Soon | NTU: I'd rather watch pain dry, okay, instead of watching this movie, okay? If you include the… instead of watching this movie, write it that your sentiment will be negative lah, okay? But since, this one doesn't say anything, so assume to be positive, okay?
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: And then for name entity, recognition, So…
Soon | NTU: Now, let's see… most stories are all the same, except, okay.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Soon, can you hear me?
Soon | NTU: Yes, yes.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: You know, I just want to ask if the outputs can be different for different, because for me, the paint one gave a negative.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: The sentiment was negative for the… What?
Soon | NTU: Sorry, can you repeat the question?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: So if you scroll up a bit, you are showing the last two, right?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: So the… the… I would rather wash the paint dry, actually gives me as a negative. So, it gave me positive, negative, negative, positive.
Soon | NTU: Okay, because a statement is not complete, okay? If you mention something like, I'd rather watch pain dry instead of watching the movie, okay, so you are putting things in the proper context for the model to understand what you're trying to mean by, I'd rather watch pain dry, right?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: No, but it's giving positive for you, but negative for me.
Soon | NTU: It is giving a… Positive sentiment, right?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: For you, for me, it's giving negative.
Soon | NTU: Oh, you're getting negative. Okay, okay.
Soon | NTU: Mmm… Are you using the same, the model that I've used?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yes, but I, I'm running it from my loadout, not from Kola.
Soon | NTU: Okay, okay, okay.
Soon | NTU: So, so… .
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: I'm running it from my, anti-gravity.
Soon | NTU: Okay, okay, yeah, yeah. Let me try to run it again, see whether I get negative.
Soon | NTU: Because this one, if the model is bad, it should know that this is a very sarcastic, right?
Soon | NTU: remark, you know, I'd rather do something else than watching this movie.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay. Thank you, thank you for your feedback, yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay, now, for the, name entity recognition, right, so I still have about 10 minutes, okay? So, name entity recognition, so instead of using the… just now, our…
Soon | NTU: The heat is…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, but for sequence classification, so now we are using a different, head, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay? We will choose to retain the body containing all the weights of the… that come with the pre-trained model, okay? So our…
Soon | NTU: NER, name entity recognition, is…
Soon | NTU: Something that we need to go into the tax provider and then start to identify which are the now and
Soon | NTU: Which are considered name entity. Okay, name entity, but… Basically now…
Soon | NTU: Now, okay, that represents, real objective leader.
Soon | NTU: person, organization, brand, location, date, time, okay? So they have a predefined category. So this is the head that we need to create, to replace the, the one that comes with the pre-trained model, okay? So we have this
Soon | NTU: It means something, right?
Soon | NTU: casing, fine-tuned… I think this one is,
Soon | NTU: It is for the type of name entity, okay? It's in English, okay? And then…
Soon | NTU: Likewise, we create a model based on this class.
Soon | NTU: And then also the tokenizer. So each model will have its own, tokenizer.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then, as you can see, if I pass a sample text like this, right, so if you were to encode this
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Using the… the… N-E-R.
Soon | NTU: Tokenizer, okay? And then you do some,
Soon | NTU: Prediction, training, okay? And then you…
Soon | NTU: will get this as a result. Okay, so what this means is, Oh, this is,
Soon | NTU: This ORG is our organization, so this one will flag this word, right?
Soon | NTU: As a name addity, okay, so I for… insane.
Soon | NTU: There is, some specific, so-called the, abbreviation, okay, eye for insight.
Soon | NTU: O… I think there's an O also, O for outside, okay? So… This is for location.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is also location. Okay, so as you can see, by giving a sentence like this, this…
Soon | NTU: your custom model is able to identify the name entity from this sentence, okay?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so name entity, recognition, usually they go with,
Soon | NTU: work together with sentiment analysis, right? So if you know this is negative sentiment, you probably want to find out what are the reasons for this customer
Soon | NTU: to be unhappy, right? So the name identity recognition probably can help you to zoom in, you know, to tell you exactly what is the cause of this negative sentiment.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so any questions, before I pass?
Soon | NTU: Over to, do you mean?
germayne: Okay… Thanks, thanks, Sol.
germayne: Okay, so I think you guys can see, from the applied standpoint, it's not that… not that difficult, right? From a code standpoint, it's actually not that… not that difficult.
germayne: Okay, let me…
germayne: Okay, so we are really approaching the end of Module 3 already. So, of course, you know, we talked so much about transformers, I definitely need to wrap up to the…
germayne: Large language models perspective, correct?
germayne: So, it's obvious that today, we can't really talk about all the different advancements, because they just keep
germayne: there's always some minor tweaks in the architecture, right? Impossible for us to cover everything.
germayne: So I think there are just certain references that, if you guys remember what I mentioned, we talked a lot about the encoder, right? But nowadays, actually, for text generation, it is actually a decoding task, right? What this means is that you… you… you have an input, which is basically your prompt.
germayne: And then when you predict the next token, you basically append the output that you do, and then you iterate repeatedly, right? It's a bit like a loop. So you loop it, and then you keep getting the next output. Of course, I'm simplifying it, there are smarter methods now, like, you know, they do speculative decoding, there has a lot of methods now to make it…
germayne: faster, but I think the endpoint here to just wrap up is that actually now people focus a lot on decoding, and decoding suddenly became very important, because
germayne: you know, when GPT blew up, everybody suddenly realized that, okay, let's just do decoder-based models, which is essentially predicting the next token.
germayne: One thing to note here is that there's a concept, internally, it uses the same mechanism
germayne: that is known as attention, but I want to talk a bit about, you know, just to wrap up, what is the difference between the decoder's attention versus the encoder's attention.
germayne: So, if you guys remember, just now we have that same text, right? So, for that same sentences, if you have robot must obey orders, so usually decoding how it works is that when the model is being trained.
germayne: The label is actually just the next word. So, robot, you predict must. Robot must, you predict obey. Robot must obey, you predict orders. Robot must obey orders, you predict end of sentence. So, you'll notice that actually, large language model is really just classification tasks.
germayne: Correct? Now you guys understand what I meant, right, at the start of the course. I say that, actually, large language model is not magic…
germayne: It's just the same thing that we learned, they just formulated it that differently. The… the concept just now, if you guys remember, that when we do… when we do attention, we are always trying to attend
germayne: The context from the words.
germayne: The only big difference here is that you notice for each row, You notice for each row.
germayne: The availability of the contacts, right, is actually limited to the token
germayne: and the previous token. And this makes sense, because if my goal is to predict the next word, I do not have access to all the words ahead. Agree?
germayne: So, previously, we saw that, you know, robot must obey, you know, I mean, we did use this example, we used the other one, the one, the second law of robotics.
germayne: You see that we can actually just do self-attention across all the words.
germayne: But for decoder, right, because you're predicting the next word, what you have available is only restricted to the word that you have, as well as the previous word. So essentially, when we calculate the attention, usually, internally, what they do is they actually compute the attention
germayne: because it's vectors, when we do the dot product, we actually calculate the vectors all at once. But then when we train the model, we need to be sure to block off the attention, so we apply what is called the attention mask. So you notice that the upper half triangle is actually being blocked. That's because the label here, mass.
germayne: I'm trying to use robot to predict mass. I must not have access to attention from the other words. I can only attend to robot.
germayne: If I want to predict obey, I only have robot mask, so on and so forth. So you notice, actually, when we calculate… the softmax here is basically the key, by the way, if you guys remember. We want to calculate the weights with respect to all the words in order to know which word is important. So you notice for each of the words, we actually mask off the words that are in the future.
germayne: And if you think about it, this is very similar to time series, where you're actually looking at some autoregressive inputs, right? You cannot look ahead, you can always… you have to look backwards.
germayne: So this is actually how the attention is actually being done during the training of large language models.
germayne: So this is the… the thing, right? So, encoder, you do self-attention, and what we call, we call this bi-directional.
germayne: Right? You're doing bi-directional attention. You attend in front, you attend behind. Right? Fantastic for encoding tasks, because at encoding, you have access to everything. But for decoding, you're always trying to predict the next word.
germayne: So, you have to do mask self-attention. Your attention is only up to the word that you have. I hope this actually makes sense.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so obviously, I think back then, before OpenAI become for-profit, everything was open source. I think up to GPT-2, everything is actually open source.
germayne: Okay? So nothing, nothing here. I think there are a lot of advancements that we are not really talking about. I think it's really a whole new topic, if you want to go very deeply.
germayne: things like the tokenizer, I believe Hugging Face actually has a lot of causes on large language model. If you're very, very interested, I would really highly suggest that you can really use all of this time to go and explore. I think by now, most of the… most of
germayne: the application perspective, people uses Hugging Face to fine-tune models and stuff.
germayne: So, yeah, so I think that's actually all, you know, we are wrapping up. I think you guys should be ready to really explore topics that are beyond what was thought, okay? There's no way I can teach you guys everything.
germayne: But I… yeah, I hope… so I presented these other results as well. So this is actually outdated already. So basically, there's this,
germayne: There's this repository, which I love it as well.
germayne: they actually implemented Lama 3 from scratch. So Lama 3, if you guys weren't aware, was one of the generation of model from Meta. So actually, if you go through the code here, you can actually get a very rough idea of the entire
germayne: large language model. And you basically see, actually, everything was taught today, right? Maybe I didn't go into the details, but everything is taught today. So, you know, you can use this to really get
germayne: some insights on, actually, what is the entire architecture for the decoder for Lama 3. Obviously, this is outdated, but
germayne: I'm still quite confident 80% of the architecture that is here is actually still relevant, okay? So I just added some extra resources, but you guys are free to really explore the… the world is your oyster, I would say, right? So you guys…
germayne: Yeah, I think that's all, that's all for today. Okay, I think there's one more section for text generation with GPT-2. I think you guys can just explore this on your own. So we are not really going to do much, it's just really loading the GPT-2 weights using Hugging Face, and then you can basically play and fine-tune the model.
germayne: Okay, so, yeah, any last questions so far? Bittersweet?
germayne: I think, I think,
germayne: We have already finished the hard stuff. I think for the next module, I think will be a lot more on the capstone, so you guys can actually choose to how to apply what you have learned.
germayne: So, yeah, I think that's the end of the journey with me, lah, with me. Not the end for you. You still have your capstone, the last portion, which I think we will introduce the next instructor, on Saturday. I think he will be present.
germayne: And we will also, like what I say, we will give some prizes to some students, okay? I have some categories for prizes for you guys.
germayne: Yeah, but I hope you guys enjoy. We can keep in touch.
germayne: Yeah, but if any question, yeah, he can just feel free to ask us.
germayne: Good.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, I mean,
germayne: kudos to you guys for really, like, going through everything. Everything is a lot of content, and yeah, I'm proud of you guys.
germayne: Okay, so I think 3.108?
germayne: Oh, wait, oh, okay, wait, sorry.
germayne: Yeah, so I think I'll see you guys on Saturday. Please come, okay? I think Saturday… please come, please come.
germayne: We can talk about other stuff.
germayne: But congrats for surviving!
germayne: Okay, so we actually finished the last topic, and I think this should actually wrap up to… Cool.
germayne: hopefully this should wrap up to, you know, some of the questions that you guys, some of the motivation that you guys might have before you join the course. Okay, so I think, hopefully, this gives you some insights on, actually, when people talk about large language models and gen AI, you know.
germayne: how does it work? I think you guys should have a better sense.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so what do you guys learn today for today's lesson?
germayne: Oh, yes, there's a 30-question assessment. I think I will release that on Saturday. Yeah, yeah, I'll give you guys that on Saturday. Yeah, don't worry, don't worry. For now.
germayne: after today, let's just have a good break, right? I think today's content is super heavy.
germayne: So, yeah, I think just give yourself a pat on the back.
germayne: Yeah, yeah, so, okay, a good, I think good takeaway for attention. So, I think, I think while you guys are writing, I'll just, like, I'll just voice over some thoughts, alright? So, I think you can think of it, of today as…
germayne: an audit of, like, how, you know, the architecture for sequential data actually moved on from RNN to LSTM to transformer, right? It's like an overview.
germayne: Where, at a breadth level, you understand the differences between each of them, correct? Just to give some notes, right, I think…
germayne: I think… I wouldn't want to say, like, LSTM is, like, totally useless, but I would say most people actually started using transformers now, as far as I know, even for time series.
germayne: Yeah? So, but still good to know, still good to know, good to know historically. If, let's say, happens, it happens to come back again, I'm sure you guys can… can understand it, yeah? But I would say majority is dominated by transformer architectures now.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, yes, I think these are, these are very, very, very good takeaways, yeah.
germayne: Okay, so which one did you think is the hardest, actually?
germayne: Do you find attention harder, or do you find the LSTM one harder, or do you find RNN harder?
germayne: So some people find RNN to be difficult. Some people say attention is difficult.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: OSTM.
germayne: I think the best is if I could take a photo of you guys when I say the LST, and then I show the equation, I remember your faces.
germayne: I think that was funny. I don't know if you guys know, you know, because I was saying, like, okay, let me just show you that, and then when I showed the equation, I could see the faces from you guys.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Yeah, okay, so I think some people find RSTM more difficult than attention.
germayne: Oh, hot.
germayne: Yeah, I mean, I gave you guys the expectation, right? Today is actually the harder, the harder topics.
germayne: Yeah, compared to the others.
germayne: And I think you guys will start to understand that actually no matter what you are trying to go into the later stuff, there's actually a story behind. Everybody started from somewhere, so then it goes along.
germayne: So I don't know, maybe 1-2 years from now, if attention changes.
germayne: Right? Somebody come up with something new. It will not be a brand new thing that is from nothing. The foundation that you have here will still matter, alright?
germayne: Okay, so how… what was the feedback for today, in terms of the content? Do you guys feel like, actually, the overall picture is good?
germayne: Do you guys think it's a bit fast?
germayne: Yeah, I think today's content is… is ambitious.
germayne: Yeah, but I… but if you were… if you were to ask me to choose, I don't think I will remove any of it, in my perspective. I think it's… it's…
germayne: is just nice, because if you remove some stuff, I think it's, it's… Not fair to the… the…
germayne: Yeah, no, but today is back, yes, yes, today is back. Zach, I think, I think has, has, has…
germayne: as much as possible, I think there are some constraints. They won't be able to increase the number of lessons. What this means is that it might get dropped.
germayne: Yeah, so that's why. But yes, I do agree. Today, the concept is…
germayne: A lot, a lot of concept, yeah?
germayne: For sure.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so what's a good takeaway today? What would you say is a good takeaway for you today?
germayne: Finally, understand the inner workings of language models.
Gwen Lim: Are there no surprise assessments of group projects?
germayne: Surprise assets, no? I mean, you guys did the assignment for Kaggle already.
germayne: No more surprise assessments.
germayne: Yeah. I think you guys are almost there already. I think the next part is really on the capstone, so it'll be all on applied.
germayne: So, I don't think there'll be so much theory. I will tell you the theory mostly. Okay, I think there are some AWS stuff, but it wouldn't be so tough. I think you guys are actually at… you guys are done.
germayne: Yeah, you guys are ready, I would say. I mean, you have to go and revise, obviously, you have to revise a lot, but you guys actually already have the idea of how things are, how things work at a very high level.
germayne: Yes, yes, yes. I'll talk about that. So I think there's this point that somebody says that I learned that there's a lot that I don't know. I want to talk about this on Saturday, not today, I'll talk about this on Saturday. Okay?
germayne: Yeah, but if today's objective, if… and I know everybody has different goals, but if your goal is to have breadth knowledge of everything, I'm sure today is good. But if you want to go very deep, you definitely need to find some time to go deeper, for sure, yeah.
germayne: But at least you know where to start, huh? Right? You know what are the terms to go into, and what to look for.
germayne: Yes.
germayne: Okay, okay, so yeah, so I think mostly you guys get a geez of what is in NLP, and NLP has changed very rapidly from 5 years ago until now. Yeah, yes, agree. The new tech is always built and…
germayne: And I think it's very important to know the story on the ones that actually came before the new tech, yeah?
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so what are the areas that you feel like will be a good area to go back and to improve on for today?
germayne: I bet you guys were right, like, revise, revise, revise. I think I've seen that, like, multiple times.
germayne: I would say one advice for you guys, right, is that if you really want to go deeper into deep learning, try to familiarize yourself from the matrix perspective.
germayne: I think if you can familiarize yourself from the matrix, it will make it a lot easier. You don't really need to go and revisit your math on, you know, every topic, but I think from the matrix perspective, if you can understand the matrix, I think that will be very helpful.
germayne: I've watched the recording 10 times. You can watch as a podcast.
germayne: Oh, yeah, yes, I think deep learning… deep learning AI, actually, basically, there's an endurance course lah, I think.
germayne: Yeah, but you will see it's actually similar. You will see it's similar. Yeah, but yes, I would highly recommend you guys to continue learning from different sources as well.
germayne: Yeah?
germayne: Yes, you can also build something with it, that's more on the applied side.
germayne: Okay, okay. Yeah, I think I've taken up, 11 minutes from you guys.
germayne: So yes, I think… I think that's all… that's all for… that's all for today's lesson. Congrats for reaching the end, and I'll see you guys on Saturday. Okay, Saturday we just have a chat. You guys can ask me any questions on career, anything. Oh, yeah, we'll do… we'll go through the summary. We'll go through the summary, the full summary for the course at the end. I'll give the mind map.
germayne: Then, yeah, I think that's all. So I'll see you guys on Saturday, but thank you.
Easwaran Jayaraman: You do, man.
Easwaran Jayaraman: Thank you.
Zac Ang: Yo.
germayne: Thank you so much. Thank you so much.
Teng Lee LIM: Thank you so much.
Josiah Ho: Yay.
germayne: Thank you, have a good night, have a good night. Thank you.
Brian Phone Myat Swe: Dude.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Bye, thank you.
germayne: Thank you.
Chieh Cheng Lai: I have one question.
germayne: Yes.
Chieh Cheng Lai: If we revise the, the notebook or any content in the lessons, if, still feel very confused, how, can I raise the question in the Discord and then address the instructor to
Chieh Cheng Lai: To explain.
germayne: I… let me, let me check what is the… but I think you guys will still keep the Discord. You guys will not exit the Discord, but let me, let me check how it will work.
germayne: Yeah, but I, yeah, let me get back on you. I think Saturday I'll get back on you on that. But you will still be in Discord, don't worry. So the support group is still there, yeah?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay, thank you.
germayne: Thank you, thank you.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, thanks a lot. Yeah, thank you so much. For exposing so much, theory on the NLP and computer vision that I never imagined.
germayne: Yeah, that's good, that's good, that's good. Thank you so much. Thank you so much, Kendra. Yep.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay, thanks, Scott.
Soon | NTU: Aye.
germayne: Okay, I'll close.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Hi, Jeremy.
germayne: Yeah, Daniel, yes, Daniel.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Is my actual persona.
germayne: Yeah?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Is it… is it common nowadays ball…
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Because today, okay, today I'll just share with you what happened.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): I got interviewed.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Agreed.
germayne: Nice! Congrats!
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): But then the trouble was the terms, I… I was not satisfied with the terms.
germayne: Oh.
germayne: Welcome.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): The tombs, the…
germayne: Oh, the contract.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): It's contract-based, what do you…
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): one-year contract. I was not satisfied with the term, so I declined the interview.
germayne: Yep.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): But I just want to find out, in the industry, because, you see, okay, the problem of a one-year contract is, let's say, let's say you…
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): For some reason, domini signals That can suddenly crop up.
germayne: Hmm.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Let's say you only have 6 months, the other 6 months, you cannot wait. Yep. The other 6 months, that's the problem of our contract.
germayne: I see.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): So, I was just wondering…
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): If I want to find a permanent tenure, it's still a contract, it's something else, or permanent tenure, right?
germayne: Hmm.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): I have to lengthen the drop shirts.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): So, this was wondering, is it common or contract-based? Because now, even teaching, because I studied math so what avenue is to be a teacher?
germayne: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. So, Daniel, so I give you some context, right? So, now in public sector, I assume your role is a public sector role, right?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Just a padre.
germayne: Yes, now they are doing contracts most of the time, yes. It's quite common for public sector.
germayne: Yes.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): But then the problem is, if, let's say you only work for 6 months, the other 6 months you cannot work, you pay back 6 months, you know.
germayne: Oh, serious I didn't know it's like that.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Contract what? Contract is that?
germayne: No, I thought contract is the same as permanent, it's just that they can don't renew your contract. It's not like you need to pay back.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Robot, the term… the mini contract means… They've been yours.
germayne: Oh, for your… for the one that you won, is it?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Most likely not, so I didn't accept those.
germayne: I see.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): I am with permanent renewal.
germayne: But contract… but contract… but from a contract perspective, doesn't mean you cannot leave, or… I don't think so, right? You can also leave when you get a contract job. You can leave.
germayne: So, I think there's different school of thoughts lah. You can also find a job first.
germayne: Then while you're on the contract job, you can always look for a different job. It's not like you are bounded to it.
germayne: Yeah, so sometimes you don't have to give up the contract just because it's contract, if you understand what I mean.
germayne: You can always get the contract first, and then while you are in the contract job, continue finding better than nothing, right?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): So by then, I'm afraid that if you leave you pay back the liquidated damages.
germayne: I don't… okay, you should double-check, I don't think all of them are like that. I don't think all of them are like that, yeah.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Oh, me, you might double check now.
germayne: Yes, you need to read the contract and double-check, yeah.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Put that much hair.
germayne: No.
germayne: So not all contract roles need to… will lock you in, as far as I understand. You can still change your job.
germayne: Yeah.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): But it depends on the job, man.
germayne: Yes, but it just means that they can choose not to renew. That's why they make it contract.
germayne: Rather than permanent.
germayne: Yeah?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Okay.
germayne: Okay, I talked to you on Saturday? Saturday? Talk to you on Saturday?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Okay, okay, okay.
Edwin Yap: domain.
germayne: Thank you, thank you, bye-bye.